<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The appollogie of the illustrious Prince Ernestus, Earle of Mansfield, &amp;c. Wherein from his first entertainment, are layd open the occasions of his warres in Bohemia, Austria, and the Palatinate, with his faithfull seruice to the King of Bohemia. Translated out of the originall French coppie.</title>
            <title>Apologie pour le tres-illustre seigneur, Ernéste conte de Mansfeld. English</title>
            <author>S. W., fl. 1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854530</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1014:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The appollogie of the illustrious Prince Ernestus, Earle of Mansfield, &amp;c. Wherein from his first entertainment, are layd open the occasions of his warres in Bohemia, Austria, and the Palatinate, with his faithfull seruice to the King of Bohemia. Translated out of the originall French coppie.</title>
                  <title>Apologie pour le tres-illustre seigneur, Ernéste conte de Mansfeld. English</title>
                  <author>S. W., fl. 1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Heidelbergh [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the readers" signed: S.W.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Apologie pour le tres-illustre seigneur, Ernéste conte de Mansfeld.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in London by Edward Allde (STC).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19956:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19956:1"/>
THE APPOLLOGIE OF THE ILLVSTRIOVS Prince ERNESTVS, Earle of <hi>Mansfield,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN FROM HIS FIRST Entertainment, are layd open the Occaſions of his Warres in <hi>Bohemia, Auſtria,</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> with his faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Originall French Coppie.</p>
            <p>Printed at Heidelbergh. 1622.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19956:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19956:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READERS.</head>
            <p>REaders you muſt giue me leaue to preſent my Booke to you, without the Epithite of Gentle, Courteous or Impartiall Readers: for mine is an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie; which, hee that is ſure of ſuch Readers, needs not make. And if the glory of this moſt loyall and victorious Count, hath ſtill at home bin confronted with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious cenſures: how ſhould a ſtory of his Actions, euery where meet with ſuch Readers? This therefore rather hopes to make, then find you ſo. And readers I call you, plurally: for it lookes to fall into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers hands, and all not alike minded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome may light vpon this Apologie, who by their enuious detractions from his Acts, haue bin the cauſers that ſome ſuch as this were ſit to bee made for his iuſtification. But I hope, that they being now out of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo no longer corriuals in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the proofe of his victorious fidelity, hath by this time either made them aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or ſilent. A ſecond ſort are thoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19956:3"/>
whom theſe ſcandalous reports haue ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended in their goood opinions of his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the King: and to them is this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology chiefly intended: for it well hopes that by relating the treacheries who (by his martiall ſentence) ſuffered for it, and withall truely repreſenting his diligence and letters to the traytors, and the wants which diſabled him from hindring their plots when his wiſdome had diſcouered them: will throughly enforme ſuch a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; turne him now to an impartial Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. A third ſort may light vpon this, who haue liued ſo farre off from newes, that they neuer heard him ſo much as ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (for thankes be to God, his glory is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trauelled then their enuy, which hath either bin loſt by the way, or turned backe againe) and I hope theſe men will thinke their money well beſtowed: in that an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology muſt of neceſſity diſcouer more priuate and particular paſſages, whence this enuy ſprang, then any generall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe <hi>Bohemian</hi> warres, need produce: for ſuch a ſtory rather relates, then proues; and beſides, here are diuers letters cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed
<pb facs="tcp:19956:3"/>
out, and letters be the very linings and inſides of Stories: and this way too, this Apology giues theſe Readers beſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction Yet for one fauour, I muſt appeale to thee Gentle and Courteous Reader, for ſo I hope euen (in this point) to finde the firſt ſort of theſe Readers; becauſe what I entreate, although it goes with the hiſtory yet it is beſides the ſcope of it, which is the thing they onely maligne: I meane to craue your fauourable cenſures, for the rudeneſſe of the Style. For wee <hi>Bohemians</hi> (next our vulgar) more frequently vſe the neighbour <hi>Italian</hi> ſpeech: but becauſe the campe (whither this is chiefely ſent) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of diuers Nations, beſt vnderſtand one another in the French, I haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wrote it in that language wherein I was leſſe perfect. But maruell not if wee Swordmen who vſe to hew out our way, now and then hacke at a word: a ſouldiers writing ſtile, is his ſtilletto, and when wee parlee, wee ſend ſummons, not orations, and their owne neceſſity perſwades the vanquiſhed to yeeld, and not the victors Rhetoricke: but if it be plaine, plainneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19956:4"/>
beſt ſets forth truth, as this is. And perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture it will be the better thought to be ſo, for the Author profeſſion: for a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier as much ſcornes to giue the lye, as to take it. Seeing then this braue mans Fame hath bin put to his compurgators: I, who haue bin a witneſſe of all I write, come in here as one of the Iurors, and vpon mine owne knowledge deliuer the truth, and (willingly) nothing but the truth: and to this I ſweare, and you here ſee I lay my hand vpon the booke. Farewell, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten after him, his owne Actions ſhall next make their owne Apology, or need none.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19956:4"/>
            <head>AN APPOLLOGIE MADE IN DEFENCE OF THE ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE, ERNESTVS Earle of MANSFIELD, Marquiſſe of CASTEL NOVO, and BONTIGLIERE, Baron of HELDRVNGEN, Marſhall of the Army of BOHEMIA, and the Prouinces <hi>Incorporated thereunto,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aſſion is a moſt ſtrange and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing; it is a malady and ſore diſeaſe of the ſoule, which hindreth the functions of Iudgement, and a miſt darkning the eyes of the Spirit, making thinges to ſeeme otherwiſe, and contrary vnto that which in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect they are. Loue the moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion of all others, thinketh that which is euill fauored to be faire, and that which is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to be good. <hi>Scilicet inſano nemo in amore videt,</hi> hatred, Enuy, and euill will, contrary paſſions, produce contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and cauſe that which is good, vertuous, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, to appeare and ſhew to be euill, vicious and worthy of blame. From thence, Ingratitude, bad ſpeeches, and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (accurſed Daughters of ſuch wicked Mothers) which ſatisfie and feede themſelues with euill, as the Spider doth with the poyſon which ſhee ſucketh out of all ſorts of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19956:5"/>
and that from the beſt, like theſe who blame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe all ſortes of actions, yea and thoſe that are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> ſo excellent a perſon, that the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Apollo</hi> was in doubt and made queſtion, whether it ſhould place him among the rancke of the Gods or of Men, what did not hee doe for the good and benefit of his natiue Countrey? and for the welfare of his fellow Cittizens? but in the meane time, they being led and carryed away by this diſeaſe, in ſtead of acknowledging his benefits imparted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ſought to doe ſome miſchiefe vnto him, charged him with many Iniuries and blowes, and finally baniſhed him out of his Countrey. The like in a manner happened vnto <hi>Scipio,</hi> hee I ſay, who by the ruyne of the <hi>Carthagian</hi> Empire, ſtrengthened the foundation of the <hi>Romane</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, his bones could finde no reſt in that place, whereunto hee had procured the ſame. <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> one of the moſt braue and valiant Princes that <hi>France</hi> euer brought forth (worthy in truth to haue Deſcended out of that moſt Illuſtrious houſe, and of a better Fortune, if it had pleaſed God to haue graunted him that fauour, as well as he had indowed him with great and rare Vertues, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and good effects witneſſed and ſet forth the greatnes of his Courage, and the affection that he bare vnto the King his Maſter. He deliuered <hi>Diſion</hi> from the ſiege that the <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> layde about it: tooke <hi>Millaine</hi> out of their handes: And which is more, aduanced the Victory, which the King had againſt them in the Battaile of <hi>Marignan.</hi> For all which his Noble actions, and many other eminent Seruices which he did for him, yet he could not obtaine his fauour. But to the contrary, the further that he proceeded, ſtill hee found himſelfe to be further from it: Paſſion hauing in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner poſſeſt the Kings minde, that he could not ſee nor behold the ſaid Princes merites, much leſſe acknowledge them: ſo that in the end, after hee had many yeares patiently borne and ſupported all the indignities, that Enuy, hatred, and euill
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19956:5"/>
will could or might ſuggeſt, Falling into deſpight and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, he ranne headlong into his owne ruyne, at the hazard of the affaires of him that was the cauſe thereof. Theſe are examples of times paſt; and now behold one of the preſent time, an Example, which ſerueth for the ſubiect of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie.</p>
            <p>The moſt Illuſtrious Prince, <hi>Erneſtus</hi> Earle of <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſield,</hi> Marquiſſe of <hi>Caſtell Nouo,</hi> and <hi>Bontighere,</hi> Baron of <hi>Heldrungen,</hi> and great Marſhall of the Army Royall, of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Prouinces incorporated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, hauing had that happy ſucceſſe, to make his Valour and Fidelity knowne vnto the Sonne of <hi>Mars, S. A. S.</hi> of <hi>Sanoy:</hi> hauing borne his Armes into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> for the ſeruice of that Crowne, made great offers vnto the ſame, expoſed his life and meanes for the good thereof, and to conclude, hauing done all that, which a great and Valiant Knight of his profeſſion could or might doe. Behold certaine euill willers, tranſported by the violence of her accurſed paſſions, ſet vpon him, and couertly vnder-hand ſeeke to vndermine the foundations of his Reputation, to make his whiteneſſe ſeeme blacke, and his fidelity ſuſpitious, blaming him, as if he had had ſome intelligence with the Enemy, that he would take his part, and afterward ſell the Towne of <hi>Pilſen</hi> when it was beſieged, vnto him for money. And in a word, they charge him with Treaſon, in ſtead of recompencing him for his Fidelity. The rumour whereof ſpread abroad through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Countrey of <hi>Bohemia, Germany, Italy,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and in all other places, Time certainely is the mother of Truth, which at the laſt although it bee hidden and couered by obſcurity, commeth forth into the light <hi>Veritatem tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus in Lucem eruit,</hi> ſaith an Ancient wiſe man. But in the meane time, he that is bitten and wounded by ſlaunder, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but feele the panges thereof, yea and in a manner dye with griefe (if it be great) if no remedy be procured for the ſame. Now as great and valiant Courages, are hardned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19956:6"/>
in greateſt dangers, and apprehend no perill, ſo they paſſe not greatly, neither yet any whit eſteeme of her woundes: accounting them to be the ſame, which they receiue by the Armes of <hi>Mars.</hi> But ſeeing that experience, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of times paſt make vs ſee and finde the contrary, and that it is a dangerous thing, to ſeeke to defend our ſelues againſt Slaunder, onely with the buckler of patience, it is requiſite to proceed with Armes, and to fight againſt this fury in the geneſis thereof. All other Armes, the more they are diſtant from the hand from whence they were ſent, ſo much the more violence and force they loſe. But thoſe of ſlaunder are cleane contrary, for the further they are from the hand, ſo much the more force they haue, and feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then to meete and encounter at handy blowes with the party. Then in ſtead of flying from them, we muſt approach neare vnto them, wee muſt caſt off our Dublets and ſhew them our naked breaſts. That is the buckler, and the Target of ſteele, which wholly and vtterly repulſeth them. That is it which wee ſhoote at in this Apologie, we ſeeke to defend the Innocency of the ſaid Prince, againſt the Impoſtures of this infernall fury, and to that end wee will produce him in open Field by the repreſentation of his valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous exploits, and by his owne permiſſion, wee will open his Dublet, and let you ſee his naked breaſt, a white breaſt, which neuer was made blacke with Infidelity, nor ſtayned with the colour of the Indian Sunne. As men know a Tree by the fruit, ſo we know a man by his workes. It is his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that wee meane, which we will make to appeare (at the leaſt in ſuch, wherein he hath had a part during this Warre) and will ſo liuely diſcribe them, one after the other, to the end that they may be ſeene of euery one, that in time to come they may be knowne by euery man, and in the end be vnto him a fortreſſe, againſt the ſlaunderous aſſaults of his euill willers. We will begin with the treaty of Conuention with the States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> made with him, and will ſet it down in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19956:6"/>
Engliſh, to ſerue for a frontiſpece, and a foundation of this worke. The tenure whereof, is as followeth.</p>
            <p>VVee <hi>N. N. N. N.</hi> the Directors and Counſellours of the Realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> thereunto Deputed with full Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power, by all the 3. Euangelicall Eſtates of this Crowne, make knowne vnto all men by theſe preſents: That foraſmuch as the ſtate of the Affaires of this Realme requireth, to prouide our ſelues of a Valiant Generall of the Artillery, and a Colonell of a certaine number of Souldiers, thereby to ſtrengthen the Armies which wee haue leuyed for the Defence of this Crowne: To that end wee haue choſen the moſt Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Erneſtus</hi> Earle of <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> Baron of <hi>Heldrungen,</hi> Colonell of the Lords, the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Electors, Princes and States of the Romane Empire, and Generall of the Germaine Troupes of <hi>S. A. S.</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> and that in regard of the good experience that hee hath had in Marſhall affaires, as alſo of other his Noble qualities: and according to the Articles made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs, haue made and declared him to bee Generall of the Artillery, and Colonell of a Regiment of Dutch Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, from two to 4000. men: to ſerue vs and the ſaid Lords of the Three Eſtates, as long as this Warre ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue. As by theſe preſents wee declare and eſtabliſh him ſo to bee, to the end that he may be knowne and holden for the ſame. In regard whereof the ſaid Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> hath offered to aſſemble his Troupes with as much ſpeed poſſible as he may or can, and of himſelfe to arme them as need requireth. And with as many Horſmen as hee can get to come hither into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to the place appointed: which when time ſerueth ſhall bee ſet downe vnto him, and at the furtheſt within Fourteene dayes, by that meanes to ſerue this Crowne, and the State thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſhall bee needfull and requiſite, and by Gods helpe to Defend the ſame, againſt all their Enemies, according to the good truſt and confidence that wee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19956:7"/>
haue repoſed in him: Aſſuring him, that wee will ſatisfie and content him, for the ſaid Offices of Generall of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilliry, and Colonell, according to the vſe and cuſtome of the Warre, and the agreement made with him, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that hee ſhall thinke himſelfe to be well pleaſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented. And further, as well for our ſelues, as for the ſaid Lords the Euangelicall States of this Crowne, wee proteſt, and promiſe to requite the good endeauours of the ſaid Earle in all occaſions, by all kindes of good Offices. In witneſſe whereof, we haue hereunto put our Seales.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Giuen in the Caſtle of</hi> Prague, <hi>in the Counſell Chamber of Vs the ſaid Directors, the</hi> 20. <hi>Day of the Month of</hi> Auguſt. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1618.</head>
               <p>THE Conditions that bound him to bring certaine Troupes thither, within a time appointed, were by him happily performed, as euery man knoweth, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Affaires will make it more euidently appeare. Now it reſteth to know, whether the ſaid Troupes were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, to the endes pretended; that is for the Defence of the ſaid Crowne: and whether he proceeded diligently and carefully in that charge which was impoſed vpon him: That is it which wee doe and will Iuſtly proue.</p>
               <p>Among the great Sea or gulfe of difficulties, whereinto the States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> found themſelues to be plunged at the beginning of their warre, there was nothing that more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them then the ſhutting vp, and ſtopping of the great paſſage into Germany: for it was from thence that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected their ayde and reliefe of munition, money and men. The Towne of <hi>Pilſen</hi> principall among the reſt, and the moſt important places of that Realme ſhut vp that paſſage. It is ten miles diſtant from <hi>Prague,</hi> vpon the great and open way
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19956:7"/>
to <hi>Nuremburg,</hi> ſeated in a plaine Countrey, riſing a little on the South ſide, betweene two ſmall Riuers, which flancke it on the Eaſt and weſt ſides, and ioyne together towards the North, garniſhed with a deepe ditch, and double walls, grounded vpon a rock, and full of a great number of Towers, with two faire Suburbs, To conclude, a Towne very ſtrong, according to the auncient manner, and found to be ſuch, by two ſieges made about the ſame, which in former time it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly ſuſtained: The firſt againſt <hi>Ziſcha, anno</hi> 1470. the other againſt the <hi>Huſsites anno</hi> 1434. which continued 10. moneths, in ſuch manner, that it had the report and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that in 700. yeares time, no man could enter into the ſame againſt her will. Beſides this, that the Towne is ſtrong, the Citizens were Catholikes, and therefore extreamely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected vnto the Emperour: as in effect they ſhewed the ſame by infinite inſolencies by them committed againſt the States, whereby they hindred them from the free vſe of that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: So that in the end, all well conſidered, ſpecially the diſcommodities which that Towne brought vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, The States reſolued to reduce the ſame vnder their obedience. And Commiſſion was giuen vnto the Earle of <hi>Mansfield,</hi> their Generall of the Artillerie, who without any delay, went and beſieged the ſame, but yet very weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ill prouided of all things neceſſary: hauing in all but nine Cornets of horſe, hired, and ſome of the Country people, and 2000. foot-men, to whom he ioyned 3. Companies more of 200. in each Company, which he raiſed during the ſiege, with ſome Companies of the Countrey people, which the States ſent vnto him. With all them, and ſixe field Peeces, (whereof the greateſt bare a bullet of fiue pound of Iron) he began the ſiege vpon the 16. of September 1618. and firſt aſſailed the Towne vpon the South ſide, (the Suburbs being burnt vp by them within the Towne,) thinking to preuaile by the aduantage of the heighth, which that ſide gaue him without: but perceiuing that it was but in vaine, he altered
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19956:8"/>
his purpoſe, and planted his Cannon againſt the Cloyſter on the Eaſt ſide, where he began to play vpon the ſame, and to ſet his Souldiers on worke both night and day, and at laſt made a breach, but ſo hard to come at, and within ſo well rampard by thoſe that were beſieged, that hee was wholly out of hope to take it on that ſide, ſpecially with thoſe ſmall field Peeces, <hi>qui vuol vada qui non vuol manda,</hi> ſaith the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian: He had written to <hi>Prague,</hi> to haue certaine peeces of greater Ordnance, but thoſe being not ſent, and perceiuing that of force he muſt haue them, or elſe leaue the ſiege, hee tooke horſe, and rode poſt to <hi>Prague,</hi> and effected ſo much, that he got two great Cannons, which hee ſpeedily brought thether: there ſtood a houſe a little beyond the breach North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, gitturing halfe without the walls, and the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarfe of the Towne: which finding fit and conuenient for his deſigne, hee cauſed it to be battered and ſuddenly with thoſe two Peeces, and the reſt that were there before, from thence beate ſo violently vpon it, that within leſſe then an houre he had made a reaſonable breach. Now in his abſence, and by commaundement from himſelfe, the Officers had ſo much annimated the Souldiers, that by extraordinary tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, they turned the ordinary courſe of the riuer, in ſuch manner, that they might goe dry-foot vnto the ſaid breach: a thing which gaue great aduantage vnto the ſaid Earle; whereof he failed not to take the benefit, and cauſed a furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſault to bee giuen, <hi>a bon chat bon Rat</hi> it is commonly ſaid; for if they without aſſayled valiantly, they within as gallantly defended themſelues, they without fought for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and they within for their liues. The breach was flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued, in ſuch manner, that they could not get vnto it; but in the face of Musket ſhot, which playd vpon them, as thick as hayle-ſhot. But the courage of that Earle, and the credit that he had with his Souldiers, made them to contemne the danger. And to conclude, after diuers houres of reſiſtance, and when they within had made all manner of reſiſtance that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19956:8"/>
poſſibly they could, it proceeded ſo farre, that they began to parley and to agree within the Towne to yeeld, with Swords in their handes, the ſaid Earle making them within to know, that he was as well able to deale fauourably, as to take aduantage of his victory by force. This was done vpon the 21. of Nouember the ſame yeare, being the firſt fruites of his labours, and newes that well pleaſed the States, who thereby perceiued themſelues to be deliuered from that troubleſome Thorne in their feete. Yet there reſted ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which wee will ſeeke to pull out, the next yeare fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, we ſhall ſee what it will be. In the meane time the ſeaſon of the yeare comming on, wee entred into Garriſon till winter was gone.</p>
               <p>Winter being paſt, the Irons began to heate, <hi>Mars</hi> with his colour euery day produced ſome other new effects. The Enemy then held no places more of importance in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but <hi>Crumaw,</hi> and <hi>Budweis,</hi> places in a manner enuironned on all ſides with our Garriſons, in ſuch manner, thus to iſſue out to forrage the Countrey, they muſt of force be ſtrong, 300. Horſmen, and 200. Muskatiers of the Enemy entred into the Field to that end. <hi>Iohn George</hi> Earle of <hi>Solmes,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell to the Generall who as then comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thoſe Garriſons, was aduertiſed thereof, and mounting on horſebacke with his Company, and a certaine number of Muskatiers, went to ſeeke the Forragers, and hauing found them, beat and wholly ouerthrew them. The ſtate of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affaires is ſubiect to change and alteration, and there is no poſperity ſo great, but either it is mixed, or elſe followed with aduerſity. Fortune enuying at the fauour which ſhee had ſhewed vnto that Lord, began to turne her backe againſt him, and prepared a croſſe for him. The 10. of Iune, <hi>anno</hi> 1619. ſhee gaue him the blowe, checke and almoſt a mate. VVe will declare the circumſtances thereof in ſome ſort, for ſpeciall cauſe.</p>
               <p>He had Commiſſion to leaue certaine men in the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19956:9"/>
for the Defence and keeping of them, and with the reſt to goe and joyne himſelfe with the Army that lay before <hi>Budweis:</hi> and in purſuite of that Commiſſion he departed from <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and went to <hi>Portewin,</hi> an houres going from <hi>Vodnian,</hi> where he attended for 500. Horſmen that the Earle was to bring vnto him; there he expected them from day to day. In the meane time the Generals preſt him to goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without ſtaying any longer for them: ſo the Tenth of the ſaid month, he departed from thence with his Troupes, being about 8. Companies of Foote, but not compleat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Garriſons aforeſaid: and about 450. Horſmen; among the ſaid Garriſons there was one of 30. Souldiers, in a Village called <hi>Netoliz,</hi> on the right hand of the way, which the Generall held. The euening before his departure, the Hungarians that ſerued the Enemy ſet Fire thereon, and conſtrained the Garriſon to withdraw themſelues into the Church. The Generall being arriued with the Army at <hi>Zablatti</hi> (in Dutch <hi>Groſſen Lasken)</hi> a Village diſtant about a Germane myle and a halfe from the ſaid <hi>Netoliz,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed by the Earle of <hi>Solmes,</hi> (who as then was at <hi>Vodnian</hi> with charge to prouide for the ſaid Garriſons) that the ſaid Souldiers yet made reſiſtance and deſired him to ayde them, to goe thither with the Army: my Lord found it to be a dangerous matter, to abandon them, he feared a reproach. Therefore he reſolued vpon another courſe, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the body of his Army to ſtay there, while he himſelfe with 150. Horſemen ranne thither, cauſing part of them to ſtay by the way, to ayde him in his retraict, and to the ſame end commanded 400. Muskatiers to march, to lye in Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado, and to ſtay his returne. He thereupon put forward with the reſt of his Horſemen, and met with the Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whom he valiantly charged, but the firſt part of them being ſeconded by a great number of others, and by ſome Troupes of <hi>Cuiraſſes,</hi> he was conſtrained to retire by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, without hauing meanes to preuaile of the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19956:9"/>
which he prouided for himſelfe by the Ambuſcado, which neuertheleſſe hee cauſed to be aduertiſed, that they ſhould ſlide along through the Wood and by the water ſide, and ſo get to the Army, which they effected in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that they ſafely arriued there, but yet were narrowly purſued by the Enemy.</p>
               <p>In the meane time, the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy</hi> with the maine body of his Army conſiſting of 5000. Horſe, and 4000. foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, marched forward, following the traces of the ſaid Lord Generall, who being come to the Village, where the reſt of his men ſtayed for him, and thinking to refreſh himſelfe, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly all the Earle of <hi>Bucquoyes</hi> Army ſhewed it ſelfe. Whereupon the Generall mounted on Horſebacke, with all his Souldiers in order of Battaile, commanded them to make a Fortification or ſconſe of Waggons, which was preſently begun on the left ſide, but by reaſon that the VVaggoners were put into a great feare by the running away of certaine Caroches, it was not made round about as it ſhould haue bin. The length of the Village was behinde at the backe of the Generals Army, his Horſemen being deuided into 3. Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, in manner of a Triangle, the better to ayde one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Foot-men were behinde, and the Carriage in the middle, being 4. Companies on the left hand and 3. on the right, and one before the Carriage, all in ſuch manner diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Horſmen had meanes to be defended by the Muskatiers. The Enemy being very neere, and all the field couered ouer with his horſemen, my Lord Generall ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that were formoſt, and ſcattered certaine Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons of Hungarians, but the <hi>Cuiraſſiers</hi> belonging to the Baron of <hi>Walſtein</hi> comming forward, he was repulſed, and ſo whotly charged on all ſides, that he was put to flight. A little before the Enemy began to giue the on-ſet, 50. Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Colonels company that were on the right ſide, were commaunded to goe to the Generals lodging, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it and the little Street betweene both: but as they went,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19956:10"/>
the reſt of the Company followed them by miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And the two other Companies did the like, and were no ſooner gone, but the Enemies entred into their places: who acknowledging and perceiuing their errour, turned backe againe, to place themſelues as they were at the firſt: but then it was too late, in ſuch manner, that they were conſtrayned to looke for their owne ſafety: There was a Wood beyond the Village, whether they ſought to retire: but finding themſelues to bee out of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, to croſſe ouer a plaine, They were preſently enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on all ſides by the Hungarians, and ſo hardly charged, that few of them could ſaue themſelues, the reſt were either ſlaine or taken priſoners. In the meane time the horſemen were broken, part of the footmen loſt, and the fiue Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies remaining in great hazard to be ſpoyled. <hi>Carpezo</hi> the Serieant Maior, the <hi>Rhingraue,</hi> The Captaines <hi>Haid, Scheam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merdorf,</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> commaunding them, had the great body of the Enemies forces before them, the fire at their backes, and all the Amunition (except ſome carkes of powder) with all the carriage burning, whereby they were put to their ſhifts, and if they had any blood at their fingers ends, it was then time for them to ſhew it, as it became them: Aſſoone as the horſemen were diſpierced, the Enemy began to ſet vpon the fiue Companies, on all ſides, where they could come at them, and they defended themſelues valiantly, as they were in a Garden, hauing the aduantage of a hedge, which was a good defence and ſafegard vnto them. The Earle of <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> made certaine peeces of Cannon to be ſhot at them on that ſide, thinking to beat it downe, but he could not doe it that day. The Sunne ſhone very hot, and the heat that encreaſed by the fire that burnt in the Village, was the cauſe that the fire which the Enemy put into the hedge, eaſily burnt: but the diligence of thoſe that were aſſayled, ſurmounting all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, preſently quenched it. In the meane time, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, without any aſtoniſhment at that diſorder; had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſembled
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19956:10"/>
and gathered his horſemen againe together, and with them forcibly paſt through the Hungarians ſquadrons, and ranne too and fro in field, and returned againe into the Village, with an intent to mount vpon a freſh horſe, and to put on his <hi>Cuiraſſe,</hi> being then vnarmed. But hee found his lodging already taken vp by the Enemy, and that ſide of the Village that was behind at the backe of his Souldiers all ſet on fire: which notwithſtanding, he ſought by all the meanes he could, to get among his footmen, but the way was ſtopt on all ſides. At the laſt, as hee turned and lookt about him to finde ſome paſſage out, he was deſired by his Officers, to regard the euident danger, whereinto he might fall, if he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there any longer, and to yeeld vnto neceſſity, to ſaue and preſerue his owne perſon, and thoſe few horſemen that were left for a better occaſion: who ſeeing that hee could doe no otherwiſe, he reſolued to retire, which he did with the point of his ſword, being enuironed, followed, and purſued by a great number of Hungarians. On the other ſide the Enemies did all what they could, to enforce the reſt of his foot-men, and they for their parts defended themſelues as well as they could. In which conflict they continued from one of the clocke in the afternoone, vntill foure of the clocke, when the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy</hi> by a Trumpet ſummoned them to yeeld. There was no apparance, that they could long deſiſt againſt ſo great an Armie. But for that the Lord Generall, as ſoone as the Enemy began to ſhew themſelues, had ſent two Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to <hi>Budweis,</hi> (which was not aboue a mile and a halfe from thence) to haue ſome ayde, they verily beleeued that it would come, and therefore would not yeeld themſelues: within an houre after he ſent another Trumpeter, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed no more then the firſt. At the laſt, betweene 7. and 8. of the clocke in the euening, hauing ſpent all their bullets, as alſo the buttons of their dublets, and their powder, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of all hope of reliefe, they yeelded vpon condition, and a ſolemne promiſe made vnto them, by the Earle of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19956:11"/>
                  <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> in faith of an honourable Knight, holding his hat in his hand, that he would keepe good quarter with them, and releaſe them all and euery one of them, paying a moneths wages for their ranſomes. A faire promiſe indeede, but badly holden. Words are feminine, and deeds maſculine: for they being carried to <hi>Crumaw,</hi> they were lodged, (being in all among others about 1200. hundred in Chambers, by great heapes together, ſo cloſe, that they could neither ſit, nor lie downe: and beſides the little pittance of victuals that was giuen them, they gaue them no drinke, which continued for certaine dayes: which they did, thereby to draw them to ſerue the Emperour, as after it happened: for when they had endured all kindes of extremities, without hauing drunke a drop of Wine or Beere for certaine dayes together, the moſt part of them yeelded vnto neceſſity. Men of good qualities, and worthy to be credited, made this report, and withall had the teſtimony of the Enemy, of that great God who knoweth all things, and of thoſe poore Souldiers, that were dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in ſuch manner. The number of the dead was eaſie to be knowne, by the number of the priſoners, the Generals Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being not aboue 1600. fighting men, horſe and foot: all the carriage was loſt, onely his owne Caroch laden with certaine thouſands of Florins, that was ſaued: which was good fortune in ſo great a misfortune, and which ſerued the ſaid Lords Generall, as an inſtrument to re-eſtabliſh his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and to ſet them on foot againe. This is the victory which hath beene reported ſo many times with great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes. The Lord Generall ſaued himſelfe from that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture, at <hi>Thein,</hi> and from thence rode to <hi>Piſeck,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken order for the Gariſons, hee returned to <hi>Pilſen,</hi> where by little and little he re-aſſembled the Souldiers that reſted of that diſcomfiture: The more that Palme is preſt downe, the higher it groweth, generous ſpirits wax bolder in aduerſities. The Generall was beaten, but not vtterly ouerthrowne, and it was not a new matter to him, to know
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19956:11"/>
that warre is variable: The warre is his practiſe, he hath vſed it from his youth vpwards, and is accuſtomed to all hazards: and as he is of a prompt and actiue nature, ſo he ſlept not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that accident, he put that money which he had left to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe, hee gaue out Commiſſions, to leuie and take vp more Souldiers in Germanie, in ſuch manner, that in the ſpace of foure or fiue weekes, hee had gotten two Regiments of foot, and a good number of horſe-men together againe. On the other ſide, the Emperours Armie daily encreaſed, in ſuch maner, that in the moneth of September, when it was at <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roditz,</hi> it was 30000. fighting men. The States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> earneſtly apprehending y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> approching of ſo puiſſant an Army, wrote in haſt to the Lord Generall to come to <hi>Prague,</hi> with all his troopes, in all chances to preſerue and defend it from an inuaſion: which was the cauſe that hee went to <hi>Veraun,</hi> from whence at laſt, by order from the ſaid States, he went to ioyne himſelfe with their great Armie. The Earle of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoy</hi> was reſolued to hazard a battaile, and to ſet vpon the <hi>Bohemians:</hi> but the Generals comming to ioyne with them, made him alter his aduiſe, ſo that within few dayes after he retired to <hi>Piſack,</hi> where he receiued newes, that <hi>Bethlem Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor</hi> was entred into the field, with a puiſſant Armie, to inuade <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in fauour of the <hi>Bohemians:</hi> So to diuert or impeach the inundation of that ſtorme; he went from <hi>Piſack</hi> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards <hi>Auſtria.</hi> The <hi>Bohemian</hi> Armie alſo breaking vp, and followed after him: at which time there was three great Armies all in the field together. I leaue the rehearſall of their proceedings, vnto thoſe that were then preſent with them, to returne to our courſe in <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the ouerthrow at <hi>Zablatti,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy</hi> being Maſter of the Field, enlarged his borders, and tooke <hi>Prachadis, Vodnian, Winterberg,</hi> and <hi>Piſacke.</hi> But then the States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> beleeuing (as it was true) that when hee was gone, It was time for them to repaire the ruines that he had made, during the time of his Victory, recalled the Lord
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19956:12"/>
Generall of the Artillery, and gaue him Commiſſion to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine thoſe places againe, and according to that Commiſſion he returned into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and with the Companies that he had left in Garriſon, and the Prince of <hi>Anholts</hi> Regiment, and ſome Troupes of horſmen, as he marched along he tooke <hi>Vodian,</hi> and ſet vpon <hi>Prachadis,</hi> and <hi>Winterbergh,</hi> one after the other, and with great agility wanne them againe. I ſaid before, that <hi>Pilſen</hi> is one of the principall places in <hi>Bohemia:</hi> and <hi>Piſacke, Tabor, Wittingaw,</hi> and <hi>Budweis,</hi> are the next. VVhereof <hi>Piſacke</hi> and <hi>Budweis,</hi> were in the Emperours power, the other two in the States hands. <hi>Piſacke</hi> being a good place, by reaſon of the ſcituation, and the walles and Ditches thereof, commaunded by a Spaniſh Captaine, that vnder him had none of the Countrey Peſants, but good Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and the time of the yeare comming on, (for it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of Nouember) it was more difficult to bee wonne, and it was thought, that that yeare it was impoſſible to be effected. And the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> finding that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price to be very difficult, wrote a Letter to the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall from <hi>Ambergh,</hi> bearing date the 15. of Nouember, in manner as followeth.</p>
               <p>MY Lord, I am of opinion and ſo ſtill continue, that your Deſigne will take no effect, for that the time of the yeare is now contrary, as alſo that the proportion of the aſſaylers, to the aſſayled, and the mutenies and Diſcords whereon you ground are vncertaine, as likewiſe that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies in this ſeaſon, making you beleeue their weakenes, will haue aduantage againſt you. But bee it as it will, if you obtaine the Victory, you ſhall deſerue to be Crowned with commendations. I pray you let me bee informed of your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19956:12"/>
proceedings at <hi>Nurembergh.</hi> If there be any man in the world who with all that hee hath, to the vttermoſt of his power, will doe you good, it is hee that is and will be my Lord.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your moſt affectionated Friend, to doe you what ſeruice he can:</hi> CHRISTIAN, <hi>Prince of</hi> Anholt.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>A great courage accompanied with a good Iudgement, effecteth ſtrange thinges, if there were difficulties: the Lord Generall of the Artillery, aſſured himſelfe to finde the meanes to ſurmount and ouercome them all, and vpon that aſſurance he went to beſiege <hi>Piſacke.</hi> But becauſe he had not ſufficient Cannot ſhot, he ſent for ſome to <hi>Prague.</hi> And in the meane time while he ſtayed for them, tenne or twelue dayes paſt ouer. When they were come, the Lord General ſet them ſo well on worke, that within few dayes after, (that is vpon the ſixth day of December) he wanne the Towne. I will not take on me to ſet downe or declare the great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of that enterpriſe. I am content to let the Reader
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19956:13"/>
know it by the Coppy of certaine Letters, that were written to the Lord Generall touching that Subiect, by the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> from <hi>Ambergh</hi> the 29. of Nouember, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>V.</hi> in manner as followeth.</p>
               <p>MY Lord, I am aboundantly wel ſatisfied with the good newes, which you haue imparted vnto mee by my Poaſt, touching the taking of <hi>Piſacke,</hi> which I eſteemed to bee very difficult, in ſo hard a time, and ſpecially in reſpect of the ſmall prouiſion, that might be ſent vnto you, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you haue once againe yeelded a proofe of your valour and vertue, which I haue preſently made knowne vnto his Maieſty, who therewith will bee exceedingly well pleaſed, and haue the greater opinion of your Valour. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well in his Maieſties name, as for my ſelfe, I giue you moſt hearty thankes, as alſo vnto all your Lieutenants, Colonels, Captaines, and all your Souldiers, for the paines, trauailes, and other endeauours by them taken and vſed in the taking of the Towne, deſiring no other, but condignly to requite them all and euery one in particular, for the ſame. And therefore I thought it good to diſpatch this preſent Bearer, to aſſure you, of the great accompt that I make of the taking of the ſaid Towne. My opinion at this preſent is, that you muſt not refraine to aſſault the Caſtle of <hi>Straconits,</hi> hauing the commodity of the Cannon ſo neare, and that there is no appearance that the Captaine therein, will long withſtand you, whome you muſt not pardon, as you did at <hi>Winterbergh.</hi> That done, you muſt looke to your Cannon, and if the wayes be too bad, you may leaue them for a while at <hi>Piſacke.</hi> But if it may bee done, I had rather they ſhould be left at <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and that they ſhould bee kept there, till I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19956:13"/>
giue you further order concerning the ſame. In the meane time, if you can affect any thing, againſt the Fortes of <hi>Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſtein</hi> as I haue heretofore written to the Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Poblis,</hi> I aſſure you, you ſhall much pleaſe his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. And in effect, it will be no ſmall matter, if you can take order there for Victuals and Munition, and that you can ſpoyle the wayes toward <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> which will put our Enemies on that ſide in diſpaire. And therewith I am of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that wee muſt content our ſelues for this Winter time, vnleſſe ſome good ſuppriſe happen by the way, which for my part I will not let ſlip, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>With another as followeth.</head>
                  <p>MY Lord, it is his Maieſty that hath written this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hereunto annexed vnto you, vpon the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment that he hath for the taking of <hi>Piſacke.</hi> It is ſaid in <hi>Nurembergh</hi> that you are able to enforce Nature. I ſend you aduiſe, &amp;c. I am, my Lord,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt affectioned Friend, to doe you any good I can:</hi> CHRISTIAN, <hi>Prince of</hi> Anholt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19956:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>His Maieſty the King of</hi> Bohemia <hi>wrote vnto him in manner as folloeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVEE yeeld thankes vnto God, for your happy ſucceſſe, and aſſure our ſelues, that of his great benignity he will further ſhew vs much more fauour, that by your Valour, great Zeale and Wiſedome, In the end wee ſhall ſee all this Realme and Countrey deliuered out of the handes of our Enemies. And as wee doe in no manner doubt, but that in all occaſions in time to come, you will make knowne the great care and vigilancy, which you haue hitherto ſhewen for the aduancement of our Seruice: So wee promiſe to acknowledge your good endeauour, by all the Fauours that wee can afford.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Nuremberg <date>
                        <hi>the laſt of Nouember,</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>St. V. FREDIRICK.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19956:14"/>
AFter all theſe exploites, the Lord Generall retired his forces into the Gariſons, the ſeaſon of the yeare in all places leſning the fury of Armes, but not the fire of iealouſie, which the ſound of his happy ſucceſſe had cauſed to riſe vp, in certaine malicious Spirits. A fire which in time to come will conſume many good Deſignes in the firſt beginning of their birth, to the great preiudice of the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia. Plinie</hi> writeth of a ſmall fiſh called <hi>Remora,</hi> and ſaith, that it is of ſuch a quality, that cleauing faſt to a Ship, though it be exceeding great, it ſtayeth the courſe thereof in the maine Seas: ſmall matters preuent great enterpriſes. Our Ship will ſet ſayle, but the ſtinking waters of euill will, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſo many <hi>Remores,</hi> that on what ſide ſo euer it ſayleth, it will hardly arriue at any good Hauen. The Reader ſhall ſee how it will fall out, by the iſſue of this diſcourſe, then let vs proceede.</p>
               <p>If it be greeuous to a particular man, to loſe that ſmall ſubſtance that he hath: It may eaſily be iudged, how much it diſpleaſeth great perſonages to loſe Crownes and whole Kingdomes. It was eaſily to be ſeene and perceiued, that <hi>Crumaw</hi> and <hi>Budweis</hi> being loſt, <hi>Bohemia</hi> would be cleane quit out of the hands of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> And that how much the more thoſe places were of great importance for the conſeruation of that Kingdome, ſo much the more, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and all the Princes of that houſe, would enforce and ſtrengthen themſelues for the maintainance of them.</p>
               <p>The Lord Generall of the Artillery foreſaw this, and that to pull thoſe two Townes out of their hands, they muſt not goe empty handed thereunto. Now for that the great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and he in <hi>Bohemia</hi> with the reſt of the Troupes, he eſteemed that the conqueſt of thoſe two Townes was reſerued for him, as the reſt of his taske. In the Winter time he began to diſpoſe of his affaires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, framed intelligences, and lent his Spirit to looke after that which in any wiſe might ſerue for the furtherance of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19956:15"/>
Deſigne. But before all things, hee ſought in good time to prouide for the aſſurance of the Towne of <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and that in time of neede he might be furniſhed with money and men. He knew the ſlackneſſe of the land Officers, and how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were to be drawne thereunto. Therefore he wrote vnto them from <hi>Pilſen,</hi> to deſire them to commaund the Countrey Peſants to trauaile about the fortification of that Towne: and to take order that it might be prouided of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition both for the belly and the warre, that hee might haue ſufficient Cannon, and Horſes to draw them into the field, and that they would ſend him money, and men to effect his Deſigne, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>They made prouiſion touching the firſt point, but ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, that in ſteed of a thouſand Peſants, that ſhould ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily haue beene employed, and changed at that worke, there was neuer aboue 300. together: for the reſt of the points, there was nothing but promiſes made in ſteed of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. The Lord Generall knowing their humours, and that if he preſt them not forwards, the matter would reſt there, ſent them Letter after Letter, the moneth of March being almoſt ſpent in following that. At laſt the ſaid Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perceiuing the ſeaſon to come on, wherein ſomething was to be done in the field, and that they went ſo ſlackly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he began againe, and writing with the beſt Inke that he could get, proteſted, that in caſe they tooke no better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for their affaires, that if any miſchiefe fell vpon them, the fault ſhould not be imputed vnto him: and that from that time forward he would diſcharge himſelfe thereof both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and all the world. Theſe proteſtations were by him reiterated diuers times one after the other, with as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſions as he could well expreſſe. In the meane time, he could not (and that with great intreaty) get but one part of that which he required, and none, or very little money. Their ordinary anſwere being, that they would take order for the ſame, withall ſtill complaining of the inſolencies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19956:15"/>
by his Souldiers. He ſtill continued his replies, and touching their complaints, ſhewed them, that without mony it was impoſſible for him, to reſtraine ſo many malcontents: and as they required that correction ſhould be inflicted on them for the ſaid inſolencies, hee ſolicited for themeanes to effect the ſame. And among other things hee propounded a courſe which is much practiſed, and common in other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and eaſily to be put in vſe among them, which was a Contribution to be raiſed vpon the Countrey Peſants, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to make an account of that which he ſhould gather, and to deduct it out of his, and his Souldiers pay. But they (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether ignorant of matters of State,) knew not how to accept of ſo good a condition, much leſſe to effect it. They rather deſired to loſe all the Countrey, then a little wealth, and all the body, rather then one member, thinking to make warre without money.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the complaints encreaſed, and from thence euill will began to ariſe, which ioyning with enuie, (whereof I haue formerly ſpoken,) will heereafter produce ſlaunders and iniuries, in effect preiudiciall both vnto the State, and to the Authors thereof. Now as we cannot denie, much leſſe excuſe the exceſſe and inſolencies, which the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as then committed, and did commit during that warre, ſo it is well knowne, that it is impoſſible to reſtraine and hold them vnder Diſcipline, if their wages be not paid them. Neither they nor their horſes can liue by the ayre, all that they haue, whether it be Armes or apparrell, weareth, waſteth, and breaketh. If they muſt buy more, they muſt haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, And if men haue it not to giue them, they will take it where they finde it, not as in part of that which is due vnto them, but without weighing or telling it. This gate being once opened vnto them, they enter into the large fields of liberty: There is no more ſtaying, nor bounds for them; in ſteed of contenting themſelues, with that whereof they haue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19956:16"/>
neede, they ſeeke to enrich themſelues thereby: they take all, force, beate, and kill thoſe that reſiſt them: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, there is no diſorder, which they will not commit, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging themſelues in their wickedneſſe, by the practiſe thereof, and frequentation with diuers Nations. The Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, the Flemming, the French man, the Italian, and the Hungarian, euery one contributeth ſomewhat of theirs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and there is no ſubtilty, nor craftineſſe, which they know not, and which they doe not put in practiſe to haue it. They ſpare no perſon of what quality ſoeuer he be, reſpect no place how holy ſo euer, neither Churches, Altars, Tombs, Sepulchres, nor the dead bodies that lye in them, can eſcape the violence of their Sacriligeous hands. Wee know and confeſſe all this, and to our great griefe haue ſeene many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples thereof. Theſe are the miſchiefes of the warre, which makes it become deteſtable, and abhominable. But what? It is not enough to know it, and to complaine thereof. Wee muſt preuent the ſame by the true and right meanes, if wee will be exempted thereof. The onely meanes to remedy all ſuch diſorders, and ſo many miſchiefes, is Diſcipline: but how ſhall it be eſtabliſhed, where money for their pay want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? I know not who would vndertake the ſame, no not the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (that great Maſter of Diſcipline) him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. In the meane time the land Officers of <hi>Bohemia</hi> taking things cleane contrary, would turne the courſe of ordinary aſtaires, and to hide and couer their ignorance, would ſerue their turnes with the cloake of pouerty, making a great ſhew and matter of the charges which they are forced to disburſe, and the ſmall meanes that they haue to defray the ſame: and when they are required to pay any money, they make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, and ſay, wee haue none, wee are not able to doe it. Thoſe that were in this Countrey during the time of peace, and that knew the riches thereof, can well iudge of the truth of ſuch an excuſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19956:16"/>
                  <hi>Bohemia</hi> is one of the beſt countries, that is to be found within the borders of great <hi>Germanie,</hi> rich of wools, corne, pearles, pretious ſtones, and of mines both of gold, ſiluer, copper, iron, lead, and all ſorts of minerals, environed with moſt rich neighbours, with whom they traffique in diuers manner, a country which of long time hath enioyed peace, and for an ornament thereof, the ordinarie ſeat of the Emperors, a place whereinto ſo great riches haue come and beene brought from all places in the world, for the ſpace of theſe 200. yeeres together. Euery man knowes the great number, and riches of the Barons and Lords of this country, there being ſome of them, that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe a million and a halfe of wealth, beſides the riches of the great Towne of <hi>Prague,</hi> without ſpeaking of the reſt. In ſuch manner, that to alledge pouertie, for enduring of a yeere and an halfes warre, it is too groſſe an excuſe, &amp; not to be allowed. But to ſay the truth, (as we ought to doe) it is the couetouſneſſe of certaine particular perſons, it is the great diſorder that was therein, touching the receiuing and diſtributing of the treaſures, which hindred them from paying the ſouldiers, that diſcipline could not be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and ſo many miſchiefes preuented. The good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had made the wolfe a ſhepherd, <hi>popel de Lobkowiz,</hi> was their Lord Treſurer, all men know his nature, and with what wood he warmes himſelfe. The three Eſtates, and the Nobilitie haue ſufficiently diſliked of his dealings. The children went to fetch muſtard. And not to hold you too long with this ſubiect, I will only ſay, that men worthy of credit, and ſuch as had that credit, to haue a ſight of the bookes of account, affirme, That ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the direction, vntill the month of Nouember, <hi>anno</hi> 1620. which is not aboue two yeeres and a halfe, the States of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> without comprehending therein the Prouinces incorporated, haue not disburſed three milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Florins. Good God, what a ſumme of money is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19956:17"/>
that, in reſpect of the great reuennes of ſo rich and opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Realme, as that is? Now let men conſider of the great ſummes of money, that haue beene leuied by contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the plaine country, and in the villages, let them only ſet downe the contributions of the Towne of <hi>Prague,</hi> and it ſhall be ſeene, whether it was for want of money, that the ſouldiers were not paid, or for want of good will. One of them of the firſt Eſtate, (for touching the two other, I am perſwaded, they did their endeuours) being asked, how much he would willingly contribute to the maintenance of the warre, out of 20000. dollars yeerely rent that he poſſeſſed, durſt offer 300. dollars a yeere. And one of the principalleſt of them, that had a great hand in managing the affaires of the Land, and one that could doe much, being rated at 2000. dollars a yeere, was willing to giue but 2. or 3. hundred a yeere. An other of the ſame coat, in ſteed of 2000. florins, that he ought for his part, would pay but 500, becauſe (as he ſaid) he had no more money. In the meane time, running away from <hi>Prague,</hi> after the battell, he left 300000. dollars ready money be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, which he could not ſaue among other things. What profit did ſome of them make, of the opening of the Emperor <hi>Rodulphus</hi> chamber? what benefit of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call goods? I will not ſpeake of the reſt. And yet they are poore, they haue no meanes to pay a little entertainment to thoſe that are ſtrangers, that haue no part of that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant riches, that daily expoſe their liues and bodies, for the good of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Crowne, and for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of thoſe, who ſo richly enioy the bleſſings of that country. Let the vnpartiall Reader, that is acquainted with the affaires of the world, iudge, if it pleaſeth him, by that which I haue ſaid, and ſhall ſay hereafter, what is the true cauſe of the diſorders and inſolencies committed by the ſouldiers, and of the miſchiefes and miſeries hapned, and fallen vpon that country. To that end, I haue made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19956:17"/>
this digreſſion. Now we will leaue theſe great maſters following their affaires in <hi>Prague,</hi> and <hi>popel de Lobkowiz</hi> telling their money, ſeparating the old groſches from the new, to melt and make his particular profit of them, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the taking of the ſaid Towne, when Colonel <hi>Iugge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es him a baſtinado, as a beginning of a reward, for his accurſed auarice. To returne vnto our purpoſe. The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, although ill prouided of that which was neceſſarie for him, yet weary to be encloſed within the walls of a Towne, and deſirous to take the aire of the fields, entred into the field, with his troupes, and ſome peeces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, in the moneth of Aprill, and marched to <hi>Grunberge,</hi> from whence he once againe gaue an other countercharge vnto the principall land officers, ſharper then the former, but to the ſame end, and then went forward. There is a Caſtle that ſtands ten miles diſtant from <hi>Prague,</hi> in the way to <hi>Vodnian</hi> and <hi>Prachadis,</hi> neere to the riuer of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauia,</hi> in a village called <hi>Thein,</hi> which as then the enemie held, and thereby much diſturbed the Kings affaires, which he determined to take from the enemie, and to that end wrote to Colonel <hi>Franc,</hi> (who as then was at <hi>Tabor,</hi> with ſix companies of Hollanders) to come with his men, and ſome troupes of horſe and foot men of the country people, vnto the ſaid village of <hi>Thein</hi> vpon a day appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and there to ſeize vpon the bridge, that ſo he might ioyne with him. Which he did, and all the troupes mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together at the time appointed in the ſaid village, in the morning when the Generall had giuen two or three volleys of Cannon ſhot at the enemie, he vnderſtood that ſome ſecond was comming to aide them, and that the vangard was already in ſight. Whereupon he cauſed his Armie to enter into the field, and placing it in order of battell, reſolued to fight, if the enemie would giue the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. Now hauing ſtaid in that manner vntill euening, and no man ſeene to appeare, and conſidering the danger that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19956:18"/>
might enſue, to lodge ſo many men in a village, and that the ſeaſon of the yeere as then was not fit to lie in the fields, as alſo the newes that came from the Earle <hi>de la Tour,</hi> who wrote for aide, he reſolued to defer that matter to a more conuenient time, and to retire to <hi>Bekin.</hi> You muſt vnderſtand, that in the meane time, the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> that was ſtrong in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> held our men at a bay, in ſuch manner, that the Earle <hi>de la Tour,</hi> who as then commanded the Armie in the abſence of the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Hohenloe,</hi> was conſtrained to ſend to the King for aide. Whereupon his Maieſtie gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Lord Generall of the Artillerie, to goe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his troupes, as he did, but againſt his will, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently foreſeeing, by experience of the time paſt, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many great perſons and commanders, iealouſie might eaſily ariſe, to the preiudice of the common good, and of ſome of them, as it hapned. When he came to <hi>Niddreller,</hi> a village two miles diſtant from <hi>Egenburg,</hi> in the lower <hi>Auſtria,</hi> where the other Armie was, he ſtayed there two or three weekes with his troupes, attending the comming of the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> Generall of all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, who as then was at <hi>Prague,</hi> in the which time he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to write againe vnto the land officers, and to harpe vpon the ſame ſtring that he had done before, withall ſhewing them of the pouertie and great neceſſitie of his ſouldiers, growing by the dearth that was in that country, all ouer-runne and ruinated by the former warres, praying and hardly preſſing them to haue a regard vnto ſo many braue men, that deſerued rather to die in battell for the Kings ſeruice, then ſo miſerably to periſh for want of food. But they were ſo farre off from hauing any regard vnto his propoſitions, that to the contrary they ſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to all the reſt of the Armie, without ſending him one penny thereof, a moſt great inequalitie, and which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him extremely. And to the purpoſe, I forgot one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19956:18"/>
important thing, which is to giue light vnto all this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but I will ſet it on worke, and place it here. The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the warre is ſuch, that when an Officer dieth, he that is next in degree after him that is dead, ſucceedeth in his place. Now the late <hi>Monſieur de fels,</hi> in his life time being Marſhall of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Armie, hauing beene ſlaine in a skirmiſh giuen by the enemie a little aboue <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genburg,</hi> the Lord Generall of the Artillery, pretended that the ſame place, eſcheated vnto him, by order of warre; and therefore wrote vnto his Maieſtie, to the land Officers, and to the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> his Generall, for the ſame; which was granted vnto him, according to his requeſt, and ſo being Marſhall of the Armie, he began to execute that Office in the Kings Campe at <hi>Egenburg,</hi> where all the Armie was lodged, &amp; continued two or three weekes without any contradiction. In the meane time, one day the Generall hauing done him that honour to come to viſit him in his lodging, told him, that in truth he had beene made Marſhall of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Armie, but that touching the office of the Marſhall of the Armie Royall, that was reſerued for the Earle of <hi>Hohenloe.</hi> Whereupon complaining of that wrong, he maintained that the ſame Office had beene abſolutely conferred vnto him, without any other condition, but only that he ſhould reſigne that of the Generall of the Artillerie: and that if he had beene told ſo much at the firſt, he would neuer haue accepted thereof, but would rather take his Office of Generall of the Artillery againe. But the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> replying, that then it was too late, becauſe the ſame was conferred to another: he ſpake no more thereof at that time, onely to conclude, he deſired the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> to giue him leaue to depart, that hee might withdraw himſelfe elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: his diſcontentment was great, but that which grieued him moſt, was, that it ſeemed vnto him, that men made more difficultie to grant him his conge
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19956:19"/>
to bee gone, then to croſſe him, and that they ſought to giue him ſo many diſcontentments, that in the end, he ſhould goe away with ſome diſgrace, by that meanes to giue the greater ſhew vnto other mens actions. Certaine dayes after the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> comming againe, into his lodging to viſit him, hee ſought to perſwade him, to content himſelfe with that Office, with the limitation aforeſaid, and to ſuffer the Earle of <hi>Hohenlo,</hi> to execute the office of Marſhall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of the Armie Royall; which he wholly refuſed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if he were but Marſhall of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Armie, he would goe thither, and being there, would obey the Earle of <hi>Hohenloe;</hi> but as Lieutenant Generall, and for that there were a great number of braue Lords, in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to command, there was no need to take any great care for him, once againe beſeeching the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> to doe him that fauour, to grant him leaue to depart. Which he gaue him. Diſcord and miſconſtring or miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of matters among domeſticall ſeruants in a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar houſe, are to be deſired for the good and profit that ariſeth thereby, vnto thoſe whom they ſerue. But diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions betweene the ſeruants of Kings and Princes, that haue the managing of affaires, cannot but be preiudiciall and hurtfull vnto their Maſters, whatſoeuer Matchiauell and others like him ſay, or diſcourſe thereof. The Lord Marſhall being already wearied with the cold anſwers, and long delaies of the land officers, &amp; grieued at the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt inequality which they vſed in the diſtribution of their monies, wrote alſo vnto them to haue leaue to depart. In the meane time there was an occaſion offered, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be fauourable vnto him, which was that newes came that <hi>Don Balthazar,</hi> being onely Commander in <hi>Bohemiah,</hi> and hauing none other there to croſſe him, was determined to iſſue out into the field, and to beſiege <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>od<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> whereupon the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> determined to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19956:19"/>
ſend ſome aide thither, and committed the charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto the Lord Marſhall, who as then tooke certaine troupes of horſe-men out of the Armie to goe with him. But before I leaue the affaires of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> I muſt touch one point more (which I had almoſt forgotten,) among the reſt of thoſe that increaſed the Lord Marſhals diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment: our Armie was lodged (as I ſaid before) about <hi>Egenburg,</hi> and the enemies toward the riuer of <hi>Danubia,</hi> within three miles of <hi>Germanie;</hi> on which ſide the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> determined ſuddenly to aſſaile it. The exploit was well and wiſely vndertaken, and dexteriouſly perſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vpon the tenth of <hi>Iune</hi> about 3. or 4. of the clocke in the euening, &amp; to that end our Armie conſiſting of 18. or 20. thouſand men, departed from the ſaid towne of <hi>Egenburg:</hi> and the next day early in the morning, got to <hi>Heiterſwrf,</hi> where the firſt quarter of the enemies Armie lay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being once diſcouered, or meeting with any ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels. Neuertheleſſe it ſtayed there, without going any further (I know not the reaſon why) and from thence returned backe againe, without performing any thing. Thoſe that then were there may if it pleaſe them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that the Lord Marſhalls ſoldiers, thought then to haue ſet forth, to giue the firſt onſet vpon the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and others that lay in that quarter, as alſo what was further done at that time. This being ſpoken to no other ende, but only to refreſh the memory of thoſe, that then were preſent there, and know what I intend to ſpeake, it being moſt certaine, that if the onſet had beene giuen, they had driuen the enemie from thence, and gotten a great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage vpon them. Now let vs proceed.</p>
               <p>The Lord Marſhall hauing receiued that commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as I ſaid before) made preparation to leaue the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, fully aſſuring himſelfe that he had already found an occaſion, by ſome notable action to make enuie it ſelfe bluſh for ſhame. It ſeemed that fortune would fauour him,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19956:20"/>
and that from thenceforth he ſhould ſaile in the ſeas of her good fauour. Yet it was but a vaine hope. The <hi>Remora</hi> cleaning faſt to the keele of our ſhip, ſtaied our courſe. The misfortune of our Realme was ſuch, that all was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to goe backward: and the moſt cleare ſighted well perceiued that hatred in the court, and enuie in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, would cauſe contrary winds to blow vpon him. He ſet ſaile in <hi>Inne;</hi> tooke his courſe through vpper <hi>Auſtria,</hi> paſt along by <hi>Wittignaw,</hi> cauſed his ſoldiers to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before the gates of <hi>Crumaw,</hi> and <hi>Budweis:</hi> to breake downe the mils about them, and to doe many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exploits: after that he came to <hi>Tabor;</hi> from thence he went to beſiege the Caſtle of <hi>Thein,</hi> which he battered, and after thirtie Voles of Cannon ſhot giuen againſt it, won it by compoſition, and by that meanes, freed the paſſage for the Kings Maieſtie from <hi>Prachadiz</hi> to <hi>Prague.</hi> Long before he had a deſigne to doe ſomething againſt <hi>Crumaw,</hi> where he had intelligences and diuers inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to become Maſter thereof: and made account to win it within few daies, if he once went to beſiege it. But two things withheld him from it, that is great want of money and men. He himſelfe, his Captaines and ſoldiers being ſo extremely needy, that they could not be more. He was brought to ſuch an exigent, that to buy victuals he was forced at times to borrow 30. or 40. Florins. To write to <hi>Prague</hi> for it, it was labour in vaine, he knew their humours too well with whom he had to deale: It was as if he ſhould beate the aire, and loſe his time, to ſeeke to doe any thing by letters. Therefore being preſt by neceſſity, and the great inſtance that his officers made vnto him, he was conſtrained to interrupt the courſe of his victory, and perſonally to goe vnto <hi>Prague,</hi> there to finde the meanes, to miniſter ſome comfort vnto his Armie, and to that end went thither, with an intent to ſtay there but 3. or 4. daies, and then to returne againe, to perſue his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19956:20"/>
But there it fell out with him, according to the manner of that court, that is, that in ſtead of foure, hee ſtaied foureteene daies.</p>
               <p>In the meane time, there hapned a little tragedie, which I will ſet downe here, becauſe in many places it hath beene diuerſly diſcourſed of, and ſpecially concerneth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the ſaid Lord Marſhall. I will tell it truly as it was. I ſaid before, that the States of nether <hi>Auſtria,</hi> had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained one of the Lord Marſhals regiments of ſoldiers into their pay. This regiment had happy and vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate ſucceſſe, as the courſe of the warre fell out. At <hi>Langenloyd</hi> the enemy comming from <hi>Crembs,</hi> to ſet vpon him that commanded the ſame in the abſence of the Lord Marſhall <hi>de fels,</hi> that was not farre from it with the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian</hi> Armie ready to aſſiſt it. But the enemie charging them with a great number of horſemen, encloſed them on all ſides, and put them to flight, euen in the face of the ſaid Lord Marſhall <hi>de fels,</hi> not without great ſuſpition of ſome ſecret conniuence. And here it is to bee noted, that the ſaid Lord Marſhall, bare a deadly hatred vnto the Earle of <hi>Mansfields</hi> ſoldiers. After that againe it had another misfortune at <hi>Garſt,</hi> whereby being ſome was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, and the ſtates of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> wanting money, they reſolued to diſcharge it, (as they did) but in the abſence of the Lord Marſhall, who tooke that their proceeding in euill part, becauſe they had promiſed, to ſend the ſaid regiment againe to him into <hi>Bohemiah,</hi> to ſerue him there where he ſhould haue occaſion to imploy it. The ſaid ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers went directly vnto <hi>Prague,</hi> there to aske for their pay; where he dealt in ſuch manner with the firſt that came thither, that they were content, giuing to ſome three, to others foure, and to ſome fiue moneths pay, to ſtay for a moneth or two for the reſt. After that came others, and among them, ſome ſeditious perſons, that would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues with the former order, but would be paid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19956:21"/>
forthwith. The Lord Marſhall ſhewed them what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and want of money he had: and that hee had not as yet receiued any thing of the States of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But all that notwithſtanding, they would not be ſatisfied, and were moſt importunate with him, ſpecially after dinner, when the ſpirit of wine had heated their braines. To conclude they reſolued to haue money, howſoeuer they came by it, and that they would not leaue the Lord Marſhals lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging before they had it. And to that end at the leaſt fifty of them in number aſſembled there together, who reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely determined to ſtay in his drawing chamber, vntill ſuch time as he came forth to ſupper, and not to leaue him till they were all paid. In the meane time the Lord Marſhall diuers times cauſed them to be ſpoken withall, and made offer vnto them of ſeuerall conditions, as alſo to ſhew them the impoſſibility that he had to pay them all at one time: for that (as it is ſaid before) he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no money from the ſtates of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But all reaſons and arguments notwithſtanding, they would haue their full and entire payment: ſaying that otherwiſe they would not depart from thence. Supper time drawing on, Two of the Lord Marſhals Captaines comming out of the chamber, thought with good ſpeeches to haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched thoſe raſcals from thence, and accommodating themſelues to neceſſity, make them leaue the place that euening, but it would not be: for in ſteed of yeelding, they became more obſtinate, and in ſtead of good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers they vſed threatnings, and ſo from words they fell to blowes. The Lord Marſhall hearing that noiſe, came forth with ſome Captaines and his houſhould ſeruants, that were about him, and ſet fiereely vpon them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they being ſomewhat abaſhed at his preſence, though they were the greater number, began to giue backe and at laſt to runne away, where many of them were hurt, and one amongſt the reſt deadly wounded. This was the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19956:21"/>
firſt act. A little while after, againe all the Captaines and officers, that then were there, thinking to goe home vnto their lodgings, and going along the ſtreetes, were ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and aſſailed by thoſe ſeditious fellowes, and driuen backe againe to the Lord Marſhals houſe. This was the ſecond act. The Captaines perceiuing what danger they were in, ſent for their Piſtols, and making themſelues ſtronger, by more officers that ioyned with them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to retire in deſpite of thoſe mutinous companions. In the meane time, it fell out that one of thoſe which held not with the ſeditious company, ſeeking to goe forward, was by them laid hold on, and hardly vſed amongſt them. The Captaines ſeeing that, ſtept forward to aide him, and charged them hotly, they for their parts likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending themſelues. Whereby on both ſides they fell at blowes. Neuertheleſſe the ſeditious ſoldiers retired, the better to rancke and fortifie themſelues. The Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall in the meane time looking out of his window, and beholding the inſolency of thoſe mutinous fellowes, went downe, and mounting vpon his horſe, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his houſhold ſeruants, ioyned with the Captaines, with whom he perſued them, and laid ſome of them dead vpon the ground. At laſt the Kings Maieſtie hearing of the quarrell, ſent his gard to aide the Lord Marſhall, and the Burgers made profer to aſſiſt him. But feare hauing already ſeized vpon the hearts of the ſeditious ſoldiers, there was nothing elſe done at that time. This was the laſt act of that Tragedie, which I haue particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, for the reaſon aforeſaid. The 14. daies being paſt, about the middle of <hi>Iune,</hi> he went from <hi>Prague,</hi> hauing firſt gotten ſome money, to comfort his ſoldiers, with promiſe ſhortly after to be better ſupplied both with men and money. And being at <hi>Thein</hi> wrote againe vnto the land Officers, and plainely made them acquainted with the neceſſity that he had of more forces, to execute his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19956:22"/>
But neuer the leſſe, to loſe no time, expecting grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forces, he went to take the fort of <hi>Walleren,</hi> after that the better to bridle other Gariſons that were neere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and ſo to prepare the way to beſiege <hi>Crumaw.</hi> Before his departure, the Earle <hi>de la Tour</hi> ſent from the Prince of <hi>Anholt,</hi> came into his Armie, and being come to <hi>Prachadiz,</hi> the Lord Marſhall receiued letters out of higher <hi>Auſtria,</hi> whereby they were intreated to goe thither, in reſpect of the danger that they feared, leaſt the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> would enter into that countrey. He ſhewed the letters vnto the Earle <hi>de la Tour,</hi> and aduiſed his Maieſtie thereof. To thoſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> hee made anſwer, that being ſo weake of forces as he was, he could not aide them, but that daily he expected more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that then he would moſt willingly come vnto them; and therewith marched forward to the fort of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leren,</hi> to beſiege it, as aforeſaid. That fort is ſeated vpon a little hill, iuſt vpon the comming out of the great wood, which is betweene <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> at the riuer of <hi>Moldauia</hi> running at the foot thereof; at the top of the ſaid fort, there was a ſmall ſconſe about 60. paces long, furniſhed with two rauelins, ſquare at both corners, which flanked the curtaines of the fort, all furniſhed with good ditches and pallizadoes, beſides the trenches that were within it. In the fort there was about 400. men. The Lord Marſhall placed his Armie about it, and not long after in the marſhie woods, by diligent ſearch, he found out a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to get neere vnto the fort on the banke ſide, and that euening he ſent one of his Captaines with 500 muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, to ſeeke to paſſe through it, &amp; to lie in the wood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the fort. The next morning the Cannon was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and two peeces and a murtherer, were ſet on worke, to hinder thoſe that were within the fort, from fortifying the ſame. About ten of the clocke, the Captaine got neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fort, and both parts ſaluting each other with a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19956:22"/>
ſtorme of musket bullets, they that were below in the halfe moone, perceiuing themſelues to be aſſailed behinde, were in great feare, and running away, ſaued themſelues in the fort; our ſouldiers purſued them hotly, and that with ſuch diligence, that preſently they got into the fort, and all the enemies were encloſed in the ſmall ſconce, well intrenched (as I ſaid before) and in an inſtant all our musketeeres got ſo neere vnto them, that they might ioyne together at puſh of pike. And in the meanetime, while the musketeers on both ſides, plaid one againſt the other, the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall cauſed a mine to be made, which the next day was blowne vp with indifferent good effect, but that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the breach was not great enough, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the next day another was begun to be made, and to conclude they within were kept at ſuch a bay with Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, Cannon ſhot, and aſſaults, that the effects thereof, ioyning with the apprehenſion which they had conceiued of another mine, the ſecond day they made compoſition, and the third day iſſued out of the fort, which according to the opinion of <hi>Don Balthaſar de Marades,</hi> Serieant Maior, Generall of the Emperors horſe-men, would haue beene ſtrong enough to haue held our Armie before it all that ſummer. The taking of this fort procured great ioy to them in <hi>Prague;</hi> but it continued not long: for in the meane time while we were buſied to pull out that thorne, the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> prickt vs with another, (hauing ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed vpon vpper <hi>Auſtria)</hi> which without compariſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured more griefe vnto vs, then euer the other did. The Lord Marſhall aduiſed his Maieſtie touching the ſame, giuing him counſell what to doe in ſuch occurrents: which becauſe it is of great importance, I will here parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſet downe the contents of his letter.</p>
               <p>SIR, yeſterday I wrote vnto your Maieſtie to certifie you of the heauy newes that is in vpper <hi>Auſtria.</hi> And for that it doth not only continue for certaine, but as it is to be feared, that the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> will approch vnto
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19956:23"/>
this country, to enter therein; I thought it conuenient to giue your Maieſtie this further aduiſe, and therewith to ſhew you what I thinke requiſite to be done in theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents. Firſt, I thinke it conuenient, and moſt neceſſarie, to prouide for the defence of the country, whereunto we are not ſufficient, when the two Regiments of the Duke <hi>de Weinmar,</hi> and that of Colonel <hi>Gray</hi> are come hither. And therefore it is requiſite, that your Maieſtie ſhould hold Colonel <hi>Grayes</hi> regiment there about <hi>Prague,</hi> for your guard, and for other occaſions, which ſhall fall out; and alſo to fortifie and keepe ſtrongly theſe foure places, <hi>Pilſen, Piſeck, Tabor,</hi> and <hi>Wittignaw;</hi> to the which end, it is requiſite, to put my Regiment into <hi>Pilſen,</hi> becauſe ſome of my men are therein already; into <hi>Piſeck</hi> the Duke <hi>de Wein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars</hi> regiment, with 100. horſemen, and 100. Hungarians; into <hi>Tabor,</hi> Colonel <hi>Francks</hi> regiment, with as many horſemen and Hungarians; and into <hi>Wittignaw,</hi> Colonel <hi>Seitans</hi> Regiment, with 50 horſemen, and 100. Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and all theſe to runne on that ſide whither the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall bend their forces, to take breath, and thereby to ſtop them (if it be poſſible) from victuals. The reſt of my horſemen, and of the Hungarians, muſt retire towards <hi>Pilſen,</hi> or to ſome other part, where occaſion ſhall ſerue; by that meanes, at times, ſuddenly to doe ſome enterpriſe, to indamage the enemie. All theſe troupes being thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, it is requiſite, that as ſoone as they are entred into the ſaid places, they muſt begin earneſtly to labour about the fortifications of the ſame; wherein your Maieſtie muſt ſpare nothing, and make as great haſte therein as poſſibly you can, becauſe it is to be feared, that we ſhall be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed ſooner then we thinke for, and that afterward it will be too late to remedie the ſame. For the enemie being ſtrong of horſemen, (as in truth he is) we may eaſily be enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him, before we could auoid it. And our forces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that manner ouerthrowne, and hauing no other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are ſtrong and well garriſond; your Maieſtie may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19956:23"/>
well iudge, what danger and loſſe may thereby enſue, and whether we may not apprehend the ſame miſchiefe to fall vpon vs, that is hapned to thoſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> ſpecially, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the mutable humor of this people, who vpon this occaſion doing ſomething to the preiudice of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, without doubt, to excuſe themſelues, will after ſeeke to couer it with the cloake of neceſſitie. But theſe foure places being fortified in this manner, that ſtorme may be ſtayed at the brinke, while the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> comes out of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to aide thoſe that are in extremitie. And by this meanes we may withſtand the enemies forces this yeere, and in the meane time your Maieſtie may haue leiſure to thinke vpon the meanes how to repulſe them altogether, better, then you can doe now. For the reſt, touching other ſmaller places, there muſt be garriſons put into them, to trouble the enemie, and ſet him on worke, and ſo to winne time. I beſeech your Maieſtie, to take a ſpeedy reſolution herein. For, firſt to write vnto the Armie, time will paſſe away. And to the contrary, If the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> ſhould not like well of this aduice, there will be time enough to alter it, and to ioyne againe. May it pleaſe your Maieſtie not to thinke ill of my boldneſſe in aduiſing you in this matter, danger and neceſſitie ioyning with the deſire, that I haue for the aduancement of your ſeruice, haue conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me thereunto, and forced me to caſt all other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations vnder foot: as alſo that neither my ſelfe, nor thoſe that are about me, can ſee any appearance at all, that with ſo ſmall forces, we may winne any honour againſt ſo puiſſant an enemie. Therefore expecting your Maieſties reſolution, alwayes vnto the laſt gaſpe of breath, I remaine your Maieſties</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Moſt humble, moſt faithfull, and moſt obedient ſeruant, <hi>Erneſtus</hi> Earle of Mansfield.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From Protowin</hi> 
                     <date> the 1. <hi>of Auguſt</hi> 1620.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19956:24"/>
This aduice was not followed, but to the contrary it was thought conuenient, to make a <hi>Campo formato.</hi> Our Armie then retired from <hi>Protwin,</hi> to <hi>Thein,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Pechin,</hi> where we continued all the month of Auguſt, increaſed by the regiments of the Duke <hi>de Saxon Weymars,</hi> and of Colonel <hi>Grayes,</hi> a Scot, and yet effected nothing, as being not ſtrong enough to withſtand ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant an enemie. During this vnprofitable ſtaying, the diſcontentment of our ſouldiers, but ſpecially that of my Lord Marſhall, increaſed more and more: becauſe, that beſides the affront that he had receiued in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſo many vaine promiſes that had beene made vnto him, by the land officers, he had alſo beene fruſtrated of meanes to effect his deſignes, without being able to doe any good for the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in time to come. In the end diſtaſting theſe things, and ſtill laden with enuie, he determined to withdraw himſelfe from thence. To that end he wrote vnto the King, and to the States, who made him a gratious anſwer, exhorting him to continue their friend, and not to abandon them in ſo troubleſome a time. Whereupon he ſent a man expreſly againe vnto the King, to let him more particularly vnderſtand his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. And in that perſute diuers meſſages were ſent and returned, and in the end it was concluded and decreed, that the States ſhould in ſhort time cauſe him to haue two months pay for his ſouldiers, and that generally his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſhould be vſed and dealt withall, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that thoſe of the great Armie were: that in reſpect of the fiue companies of horſemen that he entertained and paid out of his owne purſe, ſeeing that the Earle <hi>de la Tour</hi> had diſcharged him of two of them, that the land officers would take order, at the next meeting of the States, that he ſhould alſo be diſcharged of the three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that he ſhould execute his office of Lord Marſhall in the ſame manner that the Marſhall <hi>de Fels</hi> did, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19956:24"/>
that he ſhould not expect any order nor commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from any other then from the Lord Generall, and from ſuch as it appertained vnto. Whereupon the Lord Marſhall reſolued to continue in his Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, vntill the end of the month of October, and ſo things reſted for that time. In the meane time, this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and ſcandall was thereby raiſed, that the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall would turne his coat (as it is commonly ſaid) and ſerue the Emperor. A moſt groſſe concluſion, and ſuch as deſerued to be puniſhed in Schooles, to ſay, he will be gone and retire himſelfe out of the country, <hi>ergo,</hi> he will ioyne with the enemie, and ſerue the Emperor. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the bruit thereof hauing beene once ſpread abroad in the Citie of <hi>Prague,</hi> it afterward ranne throughout all the Realme, and further, ſpecially when it had encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with impudence, that met it in the way; and ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents ſympathizing the ſame. In ſuch manner, that in conſideration of the force which from time to time it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, by ſupport of ſo many fautors, it was apparent that in the end it would take root in his Maieſties owne chamber. But it was ſo farre from that, that that wiſe King would not once giue it any place nor entertainment into the cabinet of his conceit, but to the contrary did encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and exhort the Lord Marſhall, not to reſpect ſuch euill reports, aſſuring him of his Royall fauour, &amp;c. While we were (as I ſaid) about <hi>Berkin,</hi> the Lord Generall thought it expedient to ſend our Armie from thence, to goe to <hi>Newhats,</hi> leſt that the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> (that was not farre from thence) ſhould ſuddenly ſurprize it. And when we came thither, there we ſtayed eight or ten daies. But his Maieſtie and the land officers hauing a great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the neereneſſe of ſo many troupes, that yet were in <hi>Bava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia,</hi> and that the ſaid Duke would doe ſome enterpriſe vpon <hi>Pilſen,</hi> he commanded the Lord Marſhall to march with all his forces (as he did) to diuert, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19956:25"/>
the frontiers of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> And being on the way, he had another charge from the land officers, who (as he had already paſt by <hi>Tabor)</hi> made him make haſte, with aſſurance that his Maieſtie had proclaimed the Ban, and that all the country was vp in armes, as alſo that a great number of horſe and foot men were commanded to ioyne with him, by <hi>Glats</hi> and <hi>Taux,</hi> which they beleeued he ſhould finde there when he came thither. The cuſtome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is, that when the King goeth forth in perſon to the warre, the Earles, Barons, and Gentlemen are bound to mount on horſebacke, and to follow him; and thoſe that are called Gentlemen in that country, are at the leaſt 60000 perſons, beſides the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which are nothing ſo great a number. Now conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe great forces, and the Kings reſolution to goe perſonally into the field, the apparance was great, that they would doe ſome notable enterpriſe. Theſe great compoſed bodies, haue their ſucceſſe &amp; courſes as well as men, and are ſubiect to the ſame alterations and changes. To behold the countenances of thoſe perſonages, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that they were already rowſde out of a profound ſlumber, ſpecially hauing ſuch an alarme, as the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy</hi> made them with ſo puiſſant an Armie comming neere vnto them. We beleeued that being aſſiſted and aided by ſo great forces, we ſhould doe miracles. We did then already imagine nothing elſe, but an end of the warre. But <hi>parturiunt montes;</hi> we ſhall ſee that theſe great mountaines of promiſes, will bring forth nothing but a mouſe. In the meane time, the Lord Marſhall vnder that hope cauſed his Armie to march forward, towards <hi>Glats,</hi> and from thence about <hi>Taux,</hi> to diſcouer the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies intent, and to gouerne himſelfe thereafter. As hee marched on the way, and after he arriued there, he cauſed that aide aforeſaid to be ſought for, and nine miles all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout on this ſide to looke where thoſe ſouldiers might be,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19956:25"/>
but by no meanes could heare any newes of them: they had quartered themſelues in <hi>Eutopia,</hi> therefore it is no more ſpeaking of them. Thereupon the Lord Marſhall made complaint vnto the land officers, who for an excuſe made anſwer, that they had receiued a countermaund, and were ſent to <hi>Piſeck, Vodnian,</hi> and the places thereabouts, to ſecure them againſt <hi>Don Balthaſars</hi> forces. Whether that were true or no, we cannot tell, but it is certaine, that the enemie ſoone after wanne all thoſe places, as if no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had beene in them. Briefly, the Lord Marſhall ſeeing himſelfe deſtitute of ſuccours, and that the enemie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed cloſe vpon him: fearing leſt they ſhould take the way of <hi>Pilſen</hi> before him, reſolued to retire, and lodge there, as indeed he did. And thus ended the month of September. He being receiued, found there ſuch wants and defaults, as nothing more: the fortifications very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle furthered, want of labourers, of timber for the Palliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, and of money to ſupply all: he once againe tooke pen in hand to write to the land officers, ſhewing them of all theſe wants, and the danger they were likely to be in, if all were not ſupplied in time: But eſpecially he reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted they would ſend him in ſome munition, that he might be competently prouided to hold out a ſiege, and money to ſatisfie the officer and ſouldier: for otherwiſe it might be feared, the diſcontent already they were in, might burſt out into a mutinie, to the great preiudice of the place and cauſe. Of theſe letters he had a faire anſwer, but to no effect, according to their cuſtome. In the meane time, the Lord Marſhall, who well foreſaw, that the enemie (who had aduanc't himſelfe daily with a puiſſant Armie, forcing all the places where ere he came) would not be ſlacke to come and viſit him, did not ſleepe for his part; but made the Boores as many as he could get, to worke in the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications; and cauſed good ſtore of timber to be brought in, for the Palliſadoes, and of corne and meale, all that he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19956:26"/>
could puruey. Briefly; he did all that the time and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie required, to fortifie himſelfe againſt the enemie, who was violently comming vpon him. Neither was the enemie all this while idle, but grew ſtronger daily, by maine force making himſelfe maſter of whatſoeuer might any way oppoſe him. Then alſo <hi>Vodnian, Prachaditz, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terberg,</hi> and <hi>Piſek,</hi> were wonne with great effuſion of bloud: <hi>Schuttenhofen</hi> yeelded without ſtroke ſtriking. The like had befallen to <hi>Taux</hi> and <hi>Glatta,</hi> had not the Lord Marſhall ſtrengthned them with new ſupplies, which he had ſent in thither to lie in garriſon, ſo that the enemie found more to doethere, then at the other places. Within <hi>Taux</hi> there were two or three troupes of horſe, and ſome few foot, all commanded by the <hi>Rittmeiſter, Claudius Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaw.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">He is maſter of all the Cavaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> 
                  <hi>Don Balthaſar</hi> came hither to aſſeige it, with a great power of foot and horſe, and with 7. peeces of Cannon began to batter it, firſt on one ſide, and then on the other; they within the Towne in the meane time made it good with all their beſt endeuours. But the Towne being hard laid at on all ſides, and not well prouided of munition, and eſpecially wanting powder; after a few dayes reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, by the aduice of the ſaid Lord Marſhall, gaue it vp vpon compoſition. Into <hi>Glatta,</hi> the Lord Marſhall had ſent 200 musketiers, with certaine companies of land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke that were there, vnder the command of <hi>Sir Thomas Ferenz;</hi> who was charged by the Lord Marſhall, not to tyre out himſelfe, in regard the place could not be long kept; but to quit it, before he was driuen to extremities, leſt they ſhould loſe themſelues to no purpoſe. From <hi>Taux, Don Balthaſar</hi> went to beſiege <hi>Glatta,</hi> batterd it, and tooke it in by compoſition.</p>
               <p>His Highneſſe arriued with his Armie at <hi>Craſſitz,</hi> fiue leagues from <hi>Prague,</hi> and wrote to the Lord Marſhall the 3. of October, that he ſhould come from <hi>Pilſen</hi> with ſuch forces as he could draw out, (leauing a ſufficient garriſon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19956:26"/>
in it) to ioyne with his Armie. The day after he ſent him againe the ſame command. The Lord Marſhall doubting his Highneſſe was not throughly enough informd of the eſtate of the garriſon of <hi>Pilſen,</hi> ſent Captaine <hi>Roy,</hi> Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter generall, to ſhew him the neceſſitie the place had to keepe ſtill all the forces then within it, if they meant ſtill to hold it: offering notwithſtanding vnto his Highneſſe, that if he would appoint him the expreſſe number of men and cannon, which he would haue ſent, without leauing it to his diſcretion, he was ready to obey him. The 10. of October behold Generall <hi>Bucquoy</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> with their whole Armie, began to ſhew themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and very neere the Towne. The outworkes were not yet in caſe to be defended, nor were there forces enough to man them; beſides all other diſcommodities which vſe to fall out, where money is wanting. So as if at the inſtant, the enemie with thoſe great forces he drew af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, had attempted the place, he had certainly either carried it, or at the leaſt driuen it to ſtrange extremities. The Lord Marſhall the more leiſure he perceiued they let him haue, the more diligence he vſed. He cauſed all his ſouldiers to worke by courſe day and night in the fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; he enquired, and borrowed money of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, whereſoeuer he could finde it, to giue the ſouldier ſome content; and did ſo well and fairely, that within few dayes, the workes were defenſeable.</p>
               <p>All things going thus on, the King with his Armie was arriued at <hi>Rokezan,</hi> ſome two leagues from <hi>Pilſen,</hi> in the way towards <hi>Prague.</hi> The Count <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> a wiſe and old Captaine, ſeeing the reſolution of the Lord Marſhall; and that to force the place, would both loſe time, and many a braue man; caſt how to get it by policie;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dolus an virtus quis in hoſte requirat?</hi> and plotted how to make way into <hi>Pilſon,</hi> by ſending in thither <hi>K. Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedons</hi> mule: he had intelligence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19956:27"/>
from thence, of the ill managing of buſineſſe, amongſt ſome principall perſonages of that partie; and of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content giuen to the Lord Marſhall: and well knew, there is nothing that can put a noble ſpirit ſooner from his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture then enuie. <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ambitious, but for that, he had neuer turned the point of his ſword againſt his natiue country, if enuie had not ouercome him. And <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Burbon</hi> had neuer taken a reſolution ſo contrary to his Countries good, had he not met with this paſſion, the moſt violent of all others, and which only ouerbeares the greateſt courages. He ſtudies therefore how to gaine him that was moſt potent in that place: and whoſoeuer had voices in this counſell, held it ſo eaſie to bee brought about, that they no way doubted of the iſſue; yea they were ſo confident, that a rumor was ſpread throughout the Armie, as of a thing already done and effected. Now, notwithſtanding that the bare euent might teſtifie Ger-contrary, yet for that it is publiſhed throughout all the many, and that there is no biting of calumnie, which leaues not behinde it ſome ſcarre, to the blemiſh of his honour, that hath once beene calld in queſtion, if preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it be not waſht off with the pure ſubſtance of the truth; I would not let to ſet downe for the Reader ſo much as ſhould be neceſſarie, by the true narration of that which paſſed about this matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioachim de Carpzo,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell of one of the Regiments of my Lord Marſhall, was yet priſoner with the enemie, euer ſince the laſt ſummer, when he was taken at <hi>Glax</hi> in <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Him they made choiſe of to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of their deſigne to perſwade the Lord Marſhall to leaue the place to the Emperor, in conſideration of the reward promiſed him, which was great, as tis commonly in ſuch a caſe: in a word, mountaines of gold. He, deſirous to part from them to procure his ranſome, agreeth the willinger to take ſuch a commiſſion vpon him. But as the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19956:27"/>
common prouerbe ſaith, <hi>A thin lining agreeth not with a thin outſide.</hi> If the Count <hi>Bucquoy</hi> be honeſt, the Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is iuſt: if the one be quicke of ſight, the other is ſwift of foot. He was not ſo fooliſh, nor ſo ill a merchant, to make ſo bad a bargaine, and to ſell his honour being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, for a thing that periſheth, to looſe in one houre, what he had beene ſo long in getting, with ſuch labours and danger of his life: He had too ſtaid a iudgement, and a ſpirit better lodged, then to play ſuch a Clerkes tricke. The Count <hi>Bucquoy</hi> thought he had knowne him; but knew him not. This meſſenger then being arriued, and doing what he had in commiſſion, the Lord Marſhall ſent him preſently to his Highneſſe the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> who cauſed him to be examined by three perſons, ſet on to ſound the depth of this plot. The Lord Marſhall for his part made this occaſion of worth, to doe his Maſter ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, by whoſe conſent he gaue care to the Count <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> that he might in the while gaine time, and to make his out-workes defenceable, offers to treat with him, but vpon this condition, that firſt of all he ſhould ſee right done to the <hi>Rittmeiſter, Linſtau,</hi> whoſe troupes being gone from <hi>Heiden,</hi> in fauour of the capitulation of <hi>Taux,</hi> were ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the ſouldiers of the ſaid Count <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> who now the more to further this treatie, endeuoured by all means to giue ſatisfaction to the ſaid Captaine <hi>Linſtau.</hi> Diuers ranne vp and downe about this ſatisfaction: but ſo much time was imployed about the acceſſarie, that they had no leiſure to come to the principall. While theſe things were on foot, the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> ſent for Colonel <hi>Pobliz</hi> to come to <hi>Pilſen,</hi> vnder pretext to view the fortifications; but his meaning was, as a man may eaſily diſcerne, to get a more exact inſight into this negotiation: who being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and hauing made report of his commiſſion to his Maieſtie, his Highneſſe wrote to the Lord Marſhall, in theſe termes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19956:28"/>
My Lord: the Lord <hi>Pobliz</hi> hath well ſatisfied the King, who you may aſſure your ſelfe repoſes great confidence in you, and holds you in his good grace, &amp;c. From <hi>Rockelzan</hi> the 18. of October 1620.</p>
               <p>The next day, hee wrote to him againe, and amongſt other paſſages, one clauſe to this effect:</p>
               <p>Furthermore I am aduertiſed, when the enemie ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the treatie of <hi>Pilſen</hi> takes no effect, he will make his approch to the place, and entrench him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe about it.</p>
               <p>This is to ſhew that the Lord Marſhall did nothing in a thing of ſuch conſequence, without the aduiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Maieſtie, and his Generall. The ſame day of the ſaid month about 9. of the clocke at night, he wrote another, which I will adioyne, to the ſame end:</p>
               <p>My Lord: although I am of the ſame opinion with you, to gaine time; yet ſo it is, that his Maieſtie after he had deliberately conſidered, that of all that can happen, this is the moſt expedient; that you breake off the action: and when it be performed, that you will be pleaſed to ſend it; leauing to your diſcretion and will the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the two Companies, whereof you wrote vnto me, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is for ſubſtance the true diſcourſe of this treatie, that hath caſt ſuch miſts ouer the ignorant, and giuen ſuch hopes to the enemie. In this time were preſented ſome faire occaſions to the enemie to doe vs hurt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our want of horſe, which were all at <hi>Rokelzan</hi> in the Campe, whither the Lord Marſhall was gone to finde the King, to kiſſe his hand, and to take leaue of his Maieſtie: following the Articles of <hi>Bechin,</hi> as it came to paſſe. The Count <hi>Bucquoy</hi> perceiuing at length that golden nets would not take this Lion; and that it was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19956:28"/>
more neceſſarie to vſe his iron and ſteele, reſolued to try his force: for which purpoſe he cauſed great ſtore of faggots to be made, entending without queſtion to giue a generall aſſault. But changing his minde, he roſe with his whole Armie the twentie one of the ſaid month, to paſſe the water aboue <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and draw towards <hi>Sozer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grais,</hi> and ſo towards <hi>Prague.</hi> When he had paſſed the water, his reareward was lodged halfe an houres march from <hi>Pilſen.</hi> The next day the Count <hi>Hollach</hi> came with all the Kings horſe as well Germans as Hungarians, and with 3000. musketeers, within one houres march of <hi>Pilſen:</hi> where the Lord Marſhall meeting with him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other diſcourſes, propounded to him a meanes how to cut off the Reare of the enemie: That is, if he would pleaſe to aduance his troupes, himſelfe would ioyne with him, with the beſt that he had in <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and charging thus ioyntly the enemie, who had alſo ſome diſaduantages, they ſhould certainly beat the Reareward, or at leaſt greatly diſtreſſe them. But the Count thought it the better way to turne backe, and take the paſſage, to cut off the enemies way to <hi>Prague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Highneſſe being poſſeſt for that purpoſe of <hi>Raco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz,</hi> the two Armies houered ſome time thereabouts with various ſucceſſe, according to the courſe of the warres. At the laſt, comming ſo neere, that it was thought the Count <hi>Bucquoy</hi> would hazard a battell; his Highneſſe aduiſed the Lord Marſhall &amp; inuited him to come and attend his pleaſure, who thanked him heartily, and aſſured him, that as this was an occaſion he had alwayes ſought, ſo would he not now ſlack to put himſelfe forward with all readineſſe: for that he ſhould now be aſſured, there to be entertained in the qualitie of a Marſhall of the field, to command ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his charge; deſiring his Highneſſe that hee would ſend him word with all ſpeed, and to reſt aſſured that in ſuch a cauſe he would faile him in nothing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19956:29"/>
to loſe no more time, and withall to know the ſhort and the long, preſently after this letter he diſpatcht <hi>Sir Thomas Ferenz,</hi> with charge to ſollicite his Highneſſe in his behalfe, and to draw him to a ſpeedy reſolution. The ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Ferenz</hi> went thence poſt; but becauſe he could not haue audience of his Highneſſe all the while he was in <hi>Racoviz,</hi> hee was conſtrained to follow him to <hi>Prague;</hi> where the ouerthrow of the Armie decided the queſtion, before the ſaid <hi>Ferenz</hi> could ſpeake with his Highneſſe, and bring backe an anſwer.</p>
               <p>Vpon new buſineſſe (as we ſay) we muſt take new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations. The Lord Marſhall, hauing before taken his leaue of his Maieſtie, as was ſaid, minded nothing but his retreat: but this new accident hauing quite altred all other things, chang'd alſo his reſolution, finding himſelfe alone in <hi>Bohemia</hi> (after the other Chiefes had withdrawne themſelues) and engag'd in honour to keepe <hi>Pilſen;</hi> he caſt his eyes round about him, to ſee if there were any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of ſuccours from any part. His Highneſſe ſome dayes after the battell wrote to him, aſſuring him that ſhortly he would ſend him new directions: theſe hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected with great deuotion, ſtill hoping, they would lead him out of theſe troubles: but hauing long waited, and hearing no newes from his Highneſſe, who after that time neuer wrote him ſo much as one word, he found himſelfe by ſo much the more perplexed. The ſtopping vp of the paſſage of <hi>Germanie,</hi> from whence he only hoped to be releeued, doubled all theſe difficulties, which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues were exceeding great already. For being thus enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned on all ſides with enemies, and hauing ſmall ſtore of munition, and being bare of money, his ſouldiers ill paid, diſcontented, and which is worſe, without any hope of ſuccours, euery man may imagine in what eſtate he was. To be ſet to the helme when the winde is good, is but a pleaſure, a ſimple Pilot may then ſteere the courſe: but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19956:29"/>
when the windes are contrary, and the ſeas high-wrought, and danger ſtill thruſting vpon them, then is the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of a Maſter required.</p>
               <p>The Imperialiſts being ſeiz'd of the Towne of <hi>Prague;</hi> re-eſtabliſht (by way of diſcharge) the States in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient freedomes; and cauſed them to write to the Lord Marſhall, and to his Captaines, and ſouldiers of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Pilſen,</hi> to this purpoſe: That they would bee contented with a ſumme of money which they ſhould preſently receiue in hand, with aſſurance of the reſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and for this to render vp <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and other places vnto his Emperiall Maieſtie. Furthermore, that ſeeing the King was now retired out of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> it was in the power of the ſaid States to diſcharge the ſaid Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, ſeeing that they had entertained him of themſelues into their ſeruice, and it was to them that he had taken his oath. Theſe conditions were taken into conſideration, and to ſay truth, ſo it was, that they ſeeing no other meanes to get their pay, ſuffered themſelues to be ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerd with this offer. But the moſt part (eſpecially the Lord Marſhall) knowing that theſe were not the ſame States that had entertained them into their ſeruice; for theſe were of the religion, but thoſe, Catholicks, thought it not his beſt not to hearken to them. The Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall brought into theſe ſtreights, wrote to his Maieſtie and his Highneſſe, and to all thoſe that might be any way intereſſed in the keeping of that place, made truce with the enemie, entred a treatie with them, and to that end ſent <hi>Hieronimo de la Porta</hi> his Treaſurer to <hi>Prague.</hi> In the meane time, to eaſe himſelfe, and to diſcharge <hi>Pilſen</hi> of part of the garriſon, he billeted ſome foot and horſe in <hi>Heiden,</hi> a little Towne, where there is a reaſonable good caſtle. Thus there paſſed 5 or 6 weekes, without hearing any newes either from his Maieſtie or his Highneſſe. In the end, weighing the profit that would redound to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19956:30"/>
publique cauſe by ſtaying within <hi>Pilſen,</hi> with that which might be made by withdrawing into ſome other place; he reſolued vpon a departure, to ſee if he might either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſome way the ruinated eſtate of the preſent affaires, or elſe preſerue it from an vtter fall; he went from <hi>Pilſen</hi> with the reſt of his horſe, about the middle of December, leauing the command there to Colonel <hi>Frank,</hi> and went to take in <hi>Tachaw,</hi> then without a garriſon, and there to lodge his Cavallerie, as well to be aſſured of the paſſage from thence into the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> as alſo to enlarge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and paſſe ouer the reſt of the winter, ſo much the more comodiouſly. He wrote to <hi>Sir de Thilly</hi> Lieutenant Generall to the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and other Chiefes of the contrary party in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> to aſſure them, that this was not with any intention to breake the truce, but the better to accommodate his Cauallerie, hee wrote alſo to thoſe of <hi>Equer,</hi> who wauered already, and enclined to the Emperor, but vnderſtanding his pleaſure, they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their obedience and held firme afterward.</p>
               <p>This being done he takes his way towards <hi>Norimberg,</hi> with an intention to goe to <hi>Wormbs,</hi> to ſee the Lords the Princes; but the time being too ſhort for him, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to goe to farre from <hi>Pilſen:</hi> when he was once retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Norimberg,</hi> he diſpatcht one of his Captaines, in poſt to <hi>Wormbs:</hi> from whence being returned, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought nothing but hopes, the Lord Marſhall after he had ſent an expreſſe meſſenger to his Maieſtie, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe him of what had paſſed, he turned againe towards <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and before he arriued there he had notice giuen how all went.</p>
               <p>The enemie preuailing in his abſence, and beleeuing perchance he was gone for altogether, wrought ſecretly vpon his Captaines, thinking to corrupt them, or at leaſt to draw them to a ſpeciall treaty, contrary to that which the Lord Marſhall had begun with <hi>Bucquoy</hi> at <hi>Prague. Don</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19956:30"/>
                  <hi>Martin de Huetta</hi> Gouernour <hi>of Shuttenhofen,</hi> firſt attempted to draw ſome of them to a priuate conference, to which he being not able to bring them, or they at leaſt not at liberty to come out to him, he wrote againe to them all in generall, and more openly: That vpon conſideration of a ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they would yeeld vp themſelues and the place to the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Liechtenſtein</hi> did ſecond him with let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the ſame purpoſe. The foreſaid <hi>Hieronymo de la porta</hi> ouercome by the large promiſes of the Imperialiſts, in ſtead of doing for his Maſter as he was obliged, did for himſelfe and the aduerſe party, and wrote alſo to the ſame purpoſe: endeuouring beſide to perſwade them that the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall was gone neuer to returne againe. This letter comming from the hand of ſuch an Officer, who had ſo good reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, and meeting with humours ſymbolizing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with his intentions; I leaue it to you to iudge, whether this did ſtagger them or no.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Caſta eſt quam nemo rogauit.</head>
                  <p>Tis the tryall that makes the man knowne. This is not all. <hi>Don Martin</hi> goes further, and mixing rigor with courteſie, the rather to prouoke our Garriſon, he breakes the truce, and vſed brauing menaces and approaches, and ſo forc'd them to breake out into open hoſtility, and made pillage of all hee could get, going and comming to and from <hi>Pilſen,</hi> and in briefe did all he could to diſturbe the ſaid Garriſon. For all this the ſaid Captaines ſhrunke not for this blow: but tis well ſeene, by that which themſelues wrote to the Lord Marſhall what they would haue done, if he had not opportunely come to them, and kept vp the buſineſſe. See here the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their letter in their owne words.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19956:31"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE haue receiued a letter from your Excellencie, and vnderſtand the effects of it; whereof wee maruell much, that your Excellencie will ſtill delay the returne you promiſed vs; ſeeing we haue had a hard time of it till now. And for this one thing of keeping of good orders; ſurely tis a thing impoſſible to doe, without money; as well in reſpect of the officers as ſouldiers. Our hopes were to haue receiued in preſent pay euery Captaine 1000. florins, according to your Exc: promiſes. And for want of this, what ſhall we doe? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the enemie hath ſent out ſome troupes of horſe on euery ſide of vs, and haue taken moreouer aboue 80 of our men; although we yet know not what will be the iſſue of this truce. Behold, tis more then time for your Exc: to returne home with all ſpeed, leſt the counſell comes after the harme. The enemy threatens to keepe vs in ſo ſtrait, that we ſhall not ſafely fetch in our fewell; and if any misfortune fall out againſt our wills, we deſire to be held excuſed and blameleſſe before God and the world. On the other ſide (my Lord) we haue here a letter from his Royall Maieſtie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> directed to your Exc: but we are no wayes deſirous to be put vpon any ſeruice, till we be ſure of our pay. Moreouer, let it be taken well or ill, we are deſirous to know how the King will pay vs our old arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages. For the third: though the King would giue vs one months pay, it will not ſerue our turnes, wee cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with two. For the fourth: Foraſmuch as neither your Excellencie, nor wee the Captaines, are fauoured by the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> wee will not be commanded by him; conſidering how he hath dealt with vs both in <hi>Auſtria</hi> and here: and aboue all we intreat this; that if your Excellencie would not haue too great diſorder among the ſouldierie, let your Excellencie make all haſte to come home ſo ſoone as poſſibly, according to your High: promiſe at your departure. In thus doing, your Excellencie ſhall infinitely obligevs. No
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19956:31"/>
more at this preſent, but our prayers to God for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of your Exc: &amp;c. And ſhall euer remaine,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble and affectionate ſeruants,</signed>
                  <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Pilſen,</hi> 
                     <date>the 2 of <hi>Ianuar.</hi> 1621, <hi>ſtilo novo.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Iohann von Pierriz.</item>
                        <item>Leonhard Syrach.</item>
                        <item>Hartman Alexander von Kronniz.</item>
                        <item>Wolff Sigmund Teuffel.</item>
                        <item>Iohann Grotte.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>Poſtſcript:</head>
                  <p>My Lord, this day newes is brought that the enemie giues chaſe to our convoyes, others they diſarme, and more they take priſoners.</p>
                  <p>This letter was preſently followed by another of the ſame tenor, but much fuller of paſſion. Meane while, the Lord Marſhall tooke horſe to goe towards <hi>Tachaw,</hi> accompanied with Colonel <hi>Gray,</hi> &amp; ſome part of his <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Regiment: being there arriued, hee wrote to the ſaid Captaines, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>MY Maſters: after you had done me the honour to beare Armes vnder me, vpon ſo faire occaſions, and with ſuch reputation, I was confident you would ſo well haue obſerued my actions paſt, that you would not now haue come to this point to queſtion my ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſeeing that euery way you had leyſure to know me, that I neuer ſought but the good of euery one of you: Yet muſt I needs with great vnpleaſingneſſe take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the diſtruſt you haue of me, in a matter of ſo great conſequence as is now in hand: you lightlier giue credit to thoſe who apparantly ſeeke your ruine vnder dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conditions; then to him, who ſeekes nothing but to preſerue that honour, which you haue engaged. If I haue
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19956:32"/>
giuen my promiſe to returne, I haue kept my word: and ſee, I am comming, to doe the King ſeruice, and what ſhall be for your good, as I my ſelfe ſhall ſee occaſion, without receiuing law from you, who ought to giue it. I am now about it, nay and haue the meanes now in mine owne hands, that ſhall content you, and the whole Armie: but tis by another kinde of way, then to ſtand to their mercy, who deſire to entrap you. It is I ſay, a more honourable courſe. I had once entred into a treatie with the enemie, that we might haue got our pay that way, if we could not an other, and haue drawne our companies out from thence, where we wanted ſuccour: but ſeeing there is yet another way to come by it, and that we haue the meanes to get from thence, and that I other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where perceiue the enemie caſts about how to ouer-reach vs, I will no more of that treatie. And I cannot beleeue, that you who are bound in dutie to mee, would preferre an vncertaine profit before your honour, that ſo looſely, &amp; in ſo faire an occaſion you would forſake your Chiefe, from whom (God be praiſed) you neuer receiued diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. You haue in following that way wherein I ſet you, your pay aſſured, your liberties and honours ſafe. Wheras in place of this, from the other partie you cannot expect your pay when you are once made ſlaues, and bound hand and foot, ſo that you can haue no hope of aſſurance. Adde to this the hazard, whereinto you ſhall runne your reputations. Then if contrary to my hopes, you haue now trodden vnder foot the reſpect you owe me, &amp; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my fatherly aduiſes, you be obſtinate to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vp <hi>Pilſen,</hi> why you may do it: for my part, I will waſh my hands, and proteſt from henceforward, and hitherto, that if <hi>Pilſen</hi> be now giuen vp, it is againſt my will, my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and my commandment. Tis you that in this caſe muſt anſwer it before God, the King, and all his braue ſoldiers, ſeeing that you being not as yet forced of neceſſity, againſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19956:32"/>
all neceſſity, contrary to the will of the Chiefe, you giue ouer a place, which you before gained with ſo great glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. As for the Newes from <hi>Morania</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> with which they would ſcarre you, I wonder that like men of Spirit and experience you marke not the ſleights of a Foe, and how eaſie it is to forge ſuch ſubtle lyes, to make vſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Enemies. But if the worſt happens, what is that to vs? Tis our Honour and our pay we muſt looke after, which we are ſure to haue, if we follow good Counſaile. For we know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meanes (as I ſaid) I am preſently reſolued to fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the atchieuement, to which I inuite you alſo, That wee may hereafter performe ſome exploit, ſeruiceable to the King and our owne ſelues. And to this effect I will draw, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>From</hi> Tachaw, <hi>Ianuary</hi> 16.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſame day he wrote to Colonell</hi> Franke <hi>as followeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Sr. the further I goe the leſſe I know the reſolutions of my Captaines: I thought they had taken a good courſe, and in the meane time I ſee them ballanced in vncertainties, as if they were new commers into the world: truſting to thoſe who endeauour nothing but to enſnare them, as they may well perceiue by the Letters of the Prince of <hi>Liechtenſteim</hi> and <hi>Porta.</hi> If they purpoſe to deliuer vp <hi>Pilſen</hi> without my conſent, they may doe it. But they ſhall hazard their owne Honours and not mine. I hope as men of Honour they will haue in chiefe eſteeme that which ought to bee dearer then their very Life, and that they will conſider what may come hereafter; meane while one may ſee the fruits of theſe commers and goers, and what may come of the free acceſſe that is giuen to Enemies. And I much wonder that you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19956:33"/>
gaue addmittance into the Towne, to the Secretary or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of <hi>Porta,</hi> and ſent him not to me, ſeeing it was my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Thus if my reſolution, that Commaunding in place of my Soueraigne, I entend to bee obeyed, (as reaſon good) and to intreat you to haue a greater care hereafter, that our buſines may ſucceed better. As for going to <hi>Pilſen,</hi> I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it: but it ſhall be when I thinke good, and not at the commaund of thoſe whome I ought to Command, and who owe me farre greater reſpect then that, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In briefe, the Lord Marſhall wrote ſo often, now to one, and then to another, and followed them ſo cloſe, that at laſt he gaue them ſome aſſurance. In the meane while, making his complaints to Count <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Do Tilly</hi> of ſome wrongs done him; In that in going againſt the Truce, they ſecretly treated with his Captaines, violated his Safeguards, rob'd, tooke and kill'd his Souldiers: that the iniuries (whereof he chiefly accuſed <hi>Don Martin de Huerta)</hi> were inſupportable: that he would make himſelfe amends with the edge of his Sword, if they as Commaunders would not giue him ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Now conſidering with himſelfe the quality of the place, the ſcarcity of money, and the ſmall Companies of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers where with he was furniſhed, and that they had no like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood ſo to holde out long; He drawes out 3. Companies of Foote from <hi>Pilſen,</hi> which joyned with the Engliſh they had brought with them out of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and ſome Troupes of Horſe; He left <hi>Tachaw,</hi> and march'd towards <hi>Schakenwald,</hi> and <hi>Elenbogen,</hi> purpoſing to raiſe men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and fortifie out of hand thoſe partes that held good for the King, whereof there were a good number in thoſe parts, as <hi>Sanzen Grais,</hi> and other places thereabouts. Arriuing at <hi>Ellenbogen,</hi> he put to his vttermoſt endeauours to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion anſwerable to his Enterpriſes. And 'tis not to bee doubted, that had he beene but a little ſtronger then he was, and that the Imperialiſts had giuen him euen but a little
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19956:33"/>
time to Fortifie himſelfe, hee would haue ſtrangely encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Forces there, in regard of the good affection of the people thereabouts to his party, and the Wealth there yet left.</p>
               <p>But the Imperialiſts ſeeing what was indeed to be feared, and that this fire muſt be quencht in the beginning, ſlept not for their partes, but reſolued to goe and ſet vpon, and bee Maiſters euen of his perſon, and ſo at once to make an end of the Warres. They drew out their Garriſons and march'd directly towards <hi>Heiden</hi> and <hi>Tachaw,</hi> which they tooke in at laſt by Compoſition, they within being not able to holde out. After that, gathering together from all quarters all they could, and growing dayly ſtronger and ſtronger, they aduanct towards <hi>Schakenwald</hi> to reſtore it to the Emperors obedience.</p>
               <p>But before they arriued there, the Baron of <hi>Greot</hi> who commaunded thoſe Troupes, wrote to the L. Marſhall at <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenbogen,</hi> and vehemently perſwaded him, to bethinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in time of his Eſtate, and to make choyſe, rather of a good accord, then againſt ſuch great Forces to weaken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The L. Marſhall, who knew the benefite of all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; to drawe out buſines to the full length, anſwered this Baron: That it was not hee who had broke this Truce, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould it belong of him, if it were not continued. And ſeeing, that hee was well perſwaded of the obſeruation of it on their parts, he would willingly harken to any propoſition.</p>
               <p>But the Baron excuſing himſelfe by his want of power, the L. Marſhall ſent one of his Trumpets to <hi>Prague</hi> to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Tilly,</hi> to obtaine ſafe Conduct for <hi>William Leininger</hi> his Auditor of the Campe, whome he had Deputed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>De Tilly,</hi> about the renuing of the Treaty. In the meane time the Imperialiſts increaſed of all hands, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in dayly ſome place or other, for that the L. Marſhall could no wayes hinder them. In the end, perceiuing they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19956:34"/>
went about to inueſt themſelues of <hi>Ellenbogen,</hi> and that it was not a Towne of ſo great receipt, as to lodge his Foot, much leſſe his Cauallery: and for that it had beene too groſſe an ouerſight in him, to ſuffer himſelfe to be taken in ſuch a toyle, he went thence the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of February in the Euening; leauing 3. Companies of Foot to guard the place; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all his Cauallery retyred into the Vpper <hi>Palatinate:</hi> hauing firſt giuen order that the Engliſh, and the reſt of the Infante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, (except one Company which ſtayed in <hi>Peska)</hi> ſhould retire into <hi>Falkenaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being arriued in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> he lodg'd there his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uallery, hauing purueyed himſelfe of what neceſſaries he thought good. Thence he went to the Dyet of the Princes and States of the Vnion at <hi>Heilbrun,</hi> accompanied with his ordinary attendance, with ſome hopes to drawe ſome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours from them. But hauing ſtayed there ſome time, he was forc'd to returne without any thing, beſides bare hopes.</p>
               <p>From thence he wrote to all thoſe that were friends to the Cauſe; and layde before them his neceſſities, and the need he had of ſuccours, which he afterward ſtill preſſed, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued alwayes with exceeding diligence; hoping thereby to mooue ſome of them, whome the loſſe of that Kingdome might concerne.</p>
               <p>In the meane while, the Enemies preuayling by his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, roued vp and downe <hi>Bohemia</hi> at pleaſure; but not being able to continue their Carreere by force of Armes, by reaſon of the hardnes of the Winter; they betooke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues once againe to their Subtilties, the bad affectioned people of our party, leading them the way to it; <hi>Hieronimo de la Porta,</hi> yet reſident in <hi>Prague</hi> in the name of the Lord Marſhall; who in ſtead of giuing accompt to his Maſter of his faithfull Seruice, to which he was by Duty bound, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in his deteſtable treaſons: And as in the former ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the L. Marſhall, he had aſſayed to ſupplant the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of our Captaines, by ſome ſecret Letters of his, ſo now
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19956:34"/>
againe, he indeauoured totally to ouerthrow it by his deuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh machinations, Ambition &amp; couetouſnes, hauing ſo bleard his eyes, that he knew neither his M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. nor that Duty wherein he was obliged vnto him. And which is worſe then all, he went not alone, but there were others beſide better practiſed at it then he, who proiected theſe miſchieuous practiſes.</p>
               <p>The Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> in ſtead of obeying the L. Marſhals Commaunds, which expreſly forbad any ſuſpected perſon, but eſpecially of the Enemies, to come within <hi>Pilſen,</hi> did all the quite contrary. All ſortes of people of the aduerſe party, had free acceſſe thither, Meſſingers, Souldiers, Officers, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, yea and their Colonels too, who all went and came freely. He himſelfe went to viſite Colonell <hi>Lindlaw</hi> in his Quarters, without leaue of the L. Marſhall. The ſaid Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Lindlaw</hi> comming alſo diuerſe times to <hi>Pilſen,</hi> was there feaſted and entertained by the ſaid Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> and the Captaines of the Garriſon with aſmuch familiarity as could be deuiſed amongſt friends of the ſame party. The L. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall who neuer miſtruſted the ſaid Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he was not yet ſented out of any) being now aduertiſed what quarter he kept with his Enemies, wrote to him, but kindly exhorting him to abſtaine hereafter from ſuch vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as might bring all his Actions into ſuſpition.</p>
               <p>As the L. Marſhall was on his way towards <hi>Heilbrun,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued Letters from his Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. wherein was confirmed vnto him the charge of Marſhall generall of the field for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Vnited Countries: with full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do all that he thought would beſt aduance the ſeruice of his Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. and the profit of the Eſtates. At his returne from <hi>Heilbrun</hi> to <hi>Amberg,</hi> he got the wind of thoſe plots &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſtill on foot in <hi>Pilſen,</hi> whereupon he wrote firſt to one, and then to another, to continue conſtant, aſſuring them he would not forſake them: and that he would find the meanes to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Pay, as alſo to relieue their neceſſities: Things going thus, came his Auditor of the Camp, who had bin at <hi>Prague,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19956:35"/>
about the buſines afore mentioned: who tolde the L. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, that to continue the Treaty, hee muſt haue a larger Warrant from him, then that he had receiued at <hi>Ellenbogen.</hi> So that the L. Marſhall cauſed one to be drawne for him, in the ampleſt manner that could be deuiſed, and renued his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions: adding to the reſt of the Articles, that the Vpper <hi>Palatinate</hi> ſhould be compriſed within the ſaid Treaty. And with this Commiſſion ſent the ſaid Auditor to <hi>Prague;</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him in charge, to ſound the depth of the enemies De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, in regard of a ſpeciall Treaty they intended to haue with the Captaines; And that he ſhould perſwade the ſaid Captaines to be conſtant in his Maieſties ſeruice. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to aduertiſe him carefully of all that paſſed. This was to make the Wolfe the Shepheard. The L. Marſhall hauing had experience of his faithfull Seruice ſome yeares, thought he had dealt vprightly in his imployment, but hee had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſupt the poyſon of infidelity, out of <hi>Portaes</hi> Cup. This was verily the ſame Auditor, but chang'd within, and quite another man from what he was before. <hi>Momus</hi> had good reaſon (in my opinion) when hee had conſidered the ſtature of Mans body, to finde fault that Nature had not made a wicket before the Heart of man, that his thoughts might be diſcouered. The want of this (if I may call it a want) hath beene the cauſe that a 1000. men haue beene deceiued by theſe Two men, in whoſe ſincerity they had good confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; not being able to ſee into their inward partes, which God hath reſerued to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>In briefe, the Enemy forwarned by the treacheries of theſe two perfidious perſons; husbanded this occaſion ſo well, that they conditioned ſecretly with the Captaines, for the yeelding vp of <hi>Pilſen;</hi> while in outward ſhew they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to deſire a Treaty with the L. Marſhall. So as the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines hauing already left the party, and gone beyond the bounds of their Duty, began now to ſpeake more openly then before; They wrote, and cauſde it to be tolde by word
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19956:35"/>
of mouth to the Marſhall, that they purpoſed to expect no longer, but would either be preſently payde, or at leaſt be aſſured of their Pay; and that if ſhortly they had not a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to their mindes, and deedes accordingly; they would prouide for themſelues. The ſaid Auditor after Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> about his laſt Commiſſion, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Lord Marſhall without effecting any thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing it, that hee was ſent backe with threats and denyed Audience: For that as he alledged, the Enemy tooke it ill, that the L. Marſhall changing the contents of his firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, had inſerted this laſt Article concerning the Vpper <hi>Palatinate,</hi> which had no depency vpon <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the troath is; that they being then aſſured of the mindes of the Captaines, cared no more to holde on the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Lord Marſhall, hauing held it with him all this while to no other end, then to ſtay him from going forward.</p>
               <p>And ſurely to confeſſe the truth, both parties although they differed in their deſires, yet were they well agreed in this, that one ſought to entrap the other. The Imperialiſts had two aduantages aboue vs; that is to ſay, Meanes, (which wee wholly wanted) and the abſence of the L. Marſhall, (not to ſpeake of the perfidiouſnes of <hi>Porta.)</hi> And thus they got the game: Now the Auditor by priuate Intelligence, aſſured the L. Marſhall of the ſecret Treaty: and that his Captaines inclined wholly to the Emperours ſide, making more of euery thing then it was: The L. Marſhall vpon theſe tidings diſpatcht Letters into all quarters, and did all he could to procure money, in ſome ſort to ſatisfie the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſire of theſe Traytors. But all in vaine. For that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which he could get, could not ſtaunch their hunger.</p>
               <p>Meane time he omitted no oportunity, which might make for the breaking off of theſe treacherous practiſes; which he thought yet had floated vpon the waues of vncertainties, and not landed at any Port, hee imployes all the pollicies, which his wiſedome or dexterity could furniſh him with.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19956:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And no doubt, it had ſucceeded well, had not (ſo vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately) theſe very agents whome he vſed, being before hand corrupted, and made the Enemies, as amongſt others, the Colonell <hi>Franke</hi> and the Auditor, whom he ſent againe to <hi>Pilſen,</hi> aſwell to obſerue more narrowly the actions of the ſaid Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> as to hinder the finall Concluſion of the treaty. The L. Marſhall aſſuring himſelfe, that he being a man knowne to all the Officers and Souldiers, and of good dexterity, would doe him able ſeruice as indeed he might haue done, had he regarded Honour aſmuch as profit. But his ill meaning was to worke cleane contrary effects. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the L. Marſhall ſent a Corporall of Captaine <hi>Becke Baſlois</hi> Company, with a packet of Letters, directed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Officers; which Packet, had verily ſtrucke the ſtroke had it beene deliuered. But this honeſt Meſſinger was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed going out of <hi>Amberg,</hi> by one of <hi>Nuremberg;</hi> ſo that entring into <hi>Bohemia</hi> he was taken by the Enemies. The Colonell <hi>Lindlaw</hi> ſent the Originals to Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> who read them, and ſent them backe without deliuering them, to whom they were directed. To conclude, all thinges went backwards, So that doe what the L. Marſhall could, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume burſt. This fire that had long been raked vp vnder the aſhes of Diſſimulation, brake out into flames of a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous treaſon.</p>
               <p>The 26. of March the Treaty long a working, was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Mies,</hi> betweene the Baron of <hi>Tilly</hi> Lieutenant ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Dukedome of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> Agent in that, aſwell in the name of his Maſter, as of the Imperiall Maieſty on the one part: and the Captaines of the Garriſon of <hi>Pilſen,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Iohn Pieritz, Leonard Syrach, Wolfe Sigiſmund, Teuffell, Iohn Grott,</hi> &amp; <hi>Magnus Laurwald,</hi> on the other party. Where amongſt other Conditions it was aſſured, that in regard of their abſolute departure from the ſaid Towne of <hi>Pilſen,</hi> the ſaid Captaines ſhould receiue 140000. Florins of his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Maieſty: which was for the 7. Companies of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19956:36"/>
to euery one 20000. Florins. Colonell <hi>Franke</hi> made this Treaty a part by himſelfe, and got promiſe of 30000. Florins, in regard of the reſtitution of <hi>Tabor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This treaty of <hi>Mies</hi> thus Concluded, was put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without delay, and theſe Marchants receiued the price of their curſed ſale, wherwith euery one departed whether he thought good. Tis true that the L. Marſhall wrote to them, euen after the Concluſion of this treaty ſome kinde Letters, thinking by faire language to drawe them into the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> But it was in vaine: their guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences had taken away their courages to come before him.</p>
               <p>His Auditor of the Campe, hauing receiued 4000. Reich Dollers (the wagcs of his Periury) which hee thought to conuay ſecretly through the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> verily beleeuing by the fineneſſe of his wit ſo to Iuſtifie the reſt of his Actions: that the L. Marſhall ſhould receiue very good ſatisfaction. Couetouſnes had ſo hood-winckt his eyes, that he thought all other men blinde.</p>
               <p>The L. Marſhall who had all this while his eyes about him, and being naturally quick-ſighted, preſently diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the money; and by the price, Iudged of the quality of the marchandiſe: He cauſed at <hi>Hirſchaw</hi> the man and money to bee Attach't, and ſent out his Proceſſe by his Captaines: by whoſe ſentence hee was Condemned to Death, and Executed according to Martiall Law. The Colonell <hi>Franke</hi> was ſtrangely aſtoniſh'd at the Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of the Auditor, and became ſo melancholy vpon it, that euery man perceiued a great change and alteration in him.</p>
               <p>The L. Marſhall being come to <hi>Ambergh,</hi> thought good to call the ſaid Colonell <hi>Franke,</hi> and brought him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord the Earle of <hi>Solmes,</hi> Vice Gouernour of the Vpper <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and my Lords the Counſell Electorate, to cleare himſelfe of what ſhould be obiected againſt him, concerning the yeelding vp of <hi>Pilſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:19956:37"/>
Being ſummonned by the Lord Marſhall, he takes his Caroach and comes thither: but being there hee was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd with ſuch a feare; that without bidding farewell hee returned haſtilyer then he came, leauing his Caroach and baggage behinde him with his Seruants. Hee got to <hi>Nurembergh,</hi> and hauing ſtayed there ſome time, he went from thence to <hi>Regenſpergh,</hi> and after to <hi>Tabor,</hi> where he had thought to be entertained into the Garriſon; But they within, hauing before receiued a Commaund from the L. Marſhall not to receiue him, would not admit him. So that hauing diuers times attempted and endeauoured by all meanes hee could deuiſe to get in; at laſt being vnable to compaſſe it, after he had tarryed ſome time in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Campe, he went to <hi>Prague,</hi> there to make his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie: where wee leaue him buſied, aſwell in iuſtifying himſelfe, as accuſing others.</p>
               <p>Captaine <hi>Syrach</hi> after the yeelding vp of the Towne, departed out of <hi>Germany</hi> towards his owne Countrey: and being come neare to <hi>Erfurt,</hi> certaine Horſmen ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his Baggage, and tooke it all away: And it is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that hee loſt the worth of 30000. Florins, which was all that himſelfe had Pillag'd and come vniuſily by in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and thus is that loſt by Robbing, which is got by Oppreſſion, that alſo goes away by the Fyfe, that comes by the Drum.</p>
               <p>By theſe Examples which I ſhew by the way, it eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeares, that Diuine Iuſtice followes not farre off to Diſloyalty and periury: But if their fellowes proſper yet, they are not therefore quite exempted from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment they deſerue. Hee is not quitted, that drawes his Halter after him. Euery thing will come in his ſeaſon, that can but ſtay his time, though God lets them alone a time, he ſhall not yet forgiue them the Debt, but they ſhall pay the principall, with the arrerages, which it may bee will amount to more then they thinke of.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19956:37"/>
Now the Enemies ſeeing themſelues freed of this thorne, and Maiſters of the place which ſo much gall'd them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued for all that to driue all the otber Garriſons Royall out of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> that they might bee ſole and peaceable poſſeſſors of that Crowne. To effect this, they went to beſiege <hi>Falkenaw,</hi> (a little Towne ſcituate betwixt <hi>Eguer</hi> and <hi>Ellenbogen)</hi> to thruſt out Colonell <hi>Gray,</hi> who was in it, with certain Companies of his owne Nation and others. They battered and aſſaulted it diuers times, and plyde it ſo cloſe, that Colonell <hi>Gray</hi> after hee had done the part of a braue Souldier many dayes, was forced to Treat with them to depart with Bagge and Baggage. This place yeelded vp, none in theſe Quarters held out but <hi>Ellenbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen;</hi> a place verily not great, yet well and ſtrongly ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Nature. Beſides, the Cittizens who were much affected to the Kings party, there were yet within it three Companies of good Souldiers. Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Orten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> a young but braue and generous Lord, by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Lord Marſhall, Commanded the Towne in the Name of his Maieſty.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Falkenaw</hi> was taken in the 1. of Aprill; they plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their ſiege before <hi>Ellenbogen</hi> the 2. of the ſame Month, where they lay till the 26. of Aprill, with as much reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and wilfulnes as could bee imagined, putting to all their Forces, vigour and Stratagems, which their Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Paſſion could furniſh them with. The Cannon played perpetually, Balles of wild-fire were flung in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly; they notwithſtanding in the Towne, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſaid Lord the Count, to continue the Seruice of his Maieſty, were not wearyed out for any labour, but the more the Enemy preſt vpon them, the more reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they beſtirred themſelues to beate him off; which they did with ſuch diligence, that had they not wanted Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they had without doubt, made good the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19956:38"/>
The Lord Marſhall, all rhe Siege did what was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuccour them, hee ſtill giuing aduice to the ſaid Lord the Count; enioyning him neuertheleſſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer befell, that in Caſe hee ſawe himſelfe preſſed, before the ſuccours came in; to Treate betimes, rather then bee brought into extremities, and ſo looſe the hope of obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an Honourable parley to ſaue the Troupes, which was a thing he deſired him aboue all.</p>
               <p>At laſt about the 26. of Aprill, the Lord Marſhall went from <hi>Turchenreut</hi> with his Army, which was but uery ſmall: with an intent to rayſe the Siege, at what rate ſoeuer it ſhould bee to the Enemies: And whileſt his Vantguard was taking the paſſage of <hi>Koningſwart</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, Ellenbogen</hi> was rendred vpon Compoſition, the ſaid Lord the Count being forced to it, for the wants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſome other inconueniences hapning amongſt the Souldiers.</p>
               <p>The Articles were Honourable, (conſidering the time) that is to ſay. That our Garriſon ſhould depart with Bag and baggage, Bullet in the mouth, Matches light, Drums beating, and Colours flying, &amp;c. But the Enemy (accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to breake his Faith to thoſe of the Religion) iuſt as they had ſerued vs at <hi>Tachaw,</hi> ſo did they them heere, for, as our men went out, they pillaged them one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. So that this particular loſſe to our people, was no leſſe ſencible to our folke, then that was to the publique.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ellenbogen</hi> being loſt, the Lord Marſhall retired againe into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> to goe on with his leuyes of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to prepare himſelfe for ſome better Deſigne: which wee leaue to others to Diſcourſe off, when time ſhall ſerue. And to conclude this Treatiſe, which was compiled to no other end (as hath beene ſaid) but truely to repreſent what hath paſſed, vnder the Commaund of the Lord Marſhall, that the impartiall Reader may Iudge,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19956:38"/>
whether rightfully or wrongfully thoſe ilwillers haue tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Fidelity.</p>
               <p>The deſire to make a Diſcouery of the Truth of theſe Rumours, hath cauſed me to make this Apologie. And ſince it is for the Truth, I haue endeauoured to follow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, the Kings high-way without ſtraying to ſlip willingly into any by pathe of lying. I take to witneſſe all thoſe, that haue any knowledge in theſe Affaires, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excluding the very Enemies, whoſe teſtimony I will not out of feare refuſe in this matter. And if it ſeemes to any, that I haue ſaid too little of theſe paſſages, or that I haue cut them off too ſhort, let them knowe; my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was no other, then ſimply to ſhew the Innocency of the Lord Marſhall, by a liuely recitall of all that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerned him: and not to offend any, by bringing in ſuch matters, as might more preiudice a third perſon, then profite the ſaid Lord.</p>
               <p>The truth (ſurely) ought to bee ſpoken, but yet in its due time: Shee hath her limites and her bounds, which it is not ſo conuenient to exceed. It contents mee to haue ſaid that, which may ſerue to the conſeruation of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Lord Marſhall; whome of all other (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out praiſing him) I deſire to touch.</p>
               <p>Tis a ſigne of Pouerty to make a man braue with bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed Cloathes; hee that is of himſelfe loaden with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Renowne; why ſhould I beg for him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? Of this if hee wants more, hee will himſelfe better purchaſe it with one blowe of his valiant Sword, then I can giue him, with a thouſand Daſhes of my rude Pen.</p>
               <p>But ſeriouſly thus much: Beholde him on Horſebacke with his Sword in his hand, followed by a number of Braue and Noble Caualiers, and ready to ruſh into the thickeſt of his Enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19956:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Take heed you Lyars and backbiters: If the truth of my Quill cannot make you looke red for ſhame, the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Arme ſhall make you looke pale for feare, yea and burſt for altogether: Let vs ſee a little what hee will doe, and by the ſucceſſe of his Noble exploits, Iudge the ſincerity of his Intentions, ſeeing it is the End that Crownes the Action.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>S. W.</hi>
               </signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:19956:39"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
